<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><article xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain-id">1233</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc-domain">treephys</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Tree Physiology</journal-title><abbrev-journal-title>Tree Physiol</abbrev-journal-title></journal-title-group><publisher><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4969554</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaid">4969554</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmcaiid">4969554</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">27174702</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/treephys/tpw017</article-id><title-group><article-title>Adaptive mechanisms and genomic plasticity for drought tolerance identified in European black poplar (<italic>Populus nigra</italic> L.)</article-title></title-group><contrib-group content-type="author"><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>Viger</surname><given-names initials="M">Maud</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1">1</xref><xref rid="AN1" ref-type="author-notes">*</xref></contrib><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names initials="HK">Hazel K</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1">1</xref><xref rid="AN1" ref-type="author-notes">*</xref></contrib><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names initials="D">David</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af3">3</xref></contrib><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>Dewoody</surname><given-names initials="J">Jennifer</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af6">6</xref></contrib><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>Trewin</surname><given-names initials="H">Harriet</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1">1</xref></contrib><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>Steenackers</surname><given-names initials="M">Marijke</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af4">4</xref></contrib><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>Bastien</surname><given-names initials="C">Catherine</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af5">5</xref></contrib><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names initials="G">Gail</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1">1</xref><xref rid="cor7" ref-type="author-notes">7</xref></contrib></contrib-group><contrib-group content-type="editor"><contrib><name name-style="western"><surname>Moshelion</surname><given-names initials="M">Menachem</given-names></name><role>handling Editor</role></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="af1"><label>1</label>Centre for Biological Sciences, University of Southampton, Life Sciences Building, Southampton SO17 1BJ, UK</aff><aff id="af2"><label>2</label>UMR Ecologie et Ecophysiologie Forestières, INRA NANCY-Lorraine, 54280 Champenoux, France</aff><aff id="af3"><label>3</label>UMR Ecologie et Ecophysiologie Forestière, Université de Lorraine, BP 239, F-54506 Vandoeuvre, France</aff><aff id="af4"><label>4</label>Ministry of the Flemish Community, Research Institute for Nature and Forest (INBO), Geraardsbergen B-9500, Belgium</aff><aff id="af5"><label>5</label>INRA, Unité de Recherche Amélioration Génétique et Physiologie Forestières, 2163 avenue de la Pomme de Pin, CS 40001 Ardon, 45075 Orléans Cedex 2, France</aff><aff id="af6"><label>6</label>Present address: USDA Forest Service, National Forest Genetics Lab, 2480 Carson Road, Placerville, CA 95667, USA</aff><author-notes><fn id="cor7"><label>7</label><p>Corresponding author (<email>g.taylor@soton.ac.uk</email>)</p></fn><fn id="AN1"><label>*</label><p>These authors contributed equally to this research.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date><day>1</day><month>8</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><volume>36</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>909</fpage><page-range>909–928</page-range><pub-history><event event-type="pmc-release"><date><day>5</day><month>8</month><year>2016</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>© The Author 2016. Published by Oxford University Press.</copyright-statement><license><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" ext-link-type="uri">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="tpw017.pdf" content-type="pmc-pdf"><?cloudpmc-path d4bd/4969554/70ed5cb300ca/tpw017.pdf?><?cloudpmc-bucket app?><?size 7887522?></self-uri><abstract id="abstract1"><title>Abstract</title><p>Summer droughts are likely to increase in frequency and intensity across Europe, yet long-lived trees may have a limited ability to tolerate drought. It is therefore critical that we improve our understanding of phenotypic plasticity to drought in natural populations for ecologically and economically important trees such as <italic>Populus nigra</italic> L. A common garden experiment was conducted using ∼500 wild <italic>P. nigra</italic> trees, collected from 11 river populations across Europe. Phenotypic variation was found across the collection, with southern genotypes from Spain and France characterized by small leaves and limited biomass production. To examine the relationship between phenotypic variation and drought tolerance, six genotypes with contrasting leaf morphologies were subjected to a water deficit experiment. ‘North eastern’ genotypes were collected at wet sites and responded to water deficit with reduced biomass growth, slow stomatal closure and reduced water use efficiency (WUE) assessed by Δ<sup>13</sup>C. In contrast, ‘southern’ genotypes originating from arid sites showed rapid stomatal closure, improved WUE and limited leaf loss. Transcriptome analyses of a genotype from Spain (Sp2, originating from an arid site) and another from northern Italy (Ita, originating from a wet site) revealed dramatic differences in gene expression response to water deficit. Transcripts controlling leaf development and stomatal patterning, including <italic>SPCH</italic>, <italic>ANT</italic>, <italic>ER</italic>, <italic>AS1</italic>, <italic>AS2</italic>, <italic>PHB</italic>, <italic>CLV1</italic>, <italic>ERL1–3</italic> and <italic>TMM</italic>, were down-regulated in Ita but not in Sp2 in response to drought.</p><sec id="kwd-group1" sec-type="kwd-group" disp-level="2"><p><bold>Keywords:</bold> carbon isotope discrimination (Δ<sup>13</sup>C), microarray, stomatal number, water deficit</p></sec></abstract><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>status</meta-name><meta-value>released</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>display-pdf</meta-name><meta-value>yes</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>is-olf</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>is-manuscript</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>is-preprint</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>is-journal-matter</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>is-scanned</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>is-retracted</meta-name><meta-value>no</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta><notes notes-type="article-notes"><sec id="historyarticle-meta1" sec-type="history" disp-level="2"><p>Received 2015 Aug 17; Accepted 2016 Feb 14; Issue date 2016 Jul.</p></sec></notes></front><body><sec id="s1" disp-level="1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Forests in Europe and elsewhere are likely to experience unprecedented rises in temperature and increases in the frequency and intensity of summer droughts in the future (<xref rid="TPW017C41" ref-type="bibr">Lindner et al. 2010</xref>, <xref rid="TPW017C36" ref-type="bibr">IPCC 2014</xref>). The capacity for long-lived forest trees to adapt to a changing climate is determined by adjustments to morphological and physiological functional traits. This phenotypic plasticity allows trees to respond to a rapidly changing climate and thus provides a mechanism for acclimation (<xref rid="TPW017C11" ref-type="bibr">Bussotti et al. 2015</xref>). Although recent droughts in Europe have had major effects on forest tree mortality (<xref rid="TPW017C65" ref-type="bibr">Solberg 2004</xref>, <xref rid="TPW017C10" ref-type="bibr">Bréda and Badeau 2008</xref>, <xref rid="TPW017C4" ref-type="bibr">Allen et al. 2010</xref>), high phenotypic plasticity could enable populations to survive in a changing environment (<xref rid="TPW017C8" ref-type="bibr">Benito Garzón et al. 2011</xref>), where moderate droughts will be increasingly common. As such, understanding phenotypic responses to drought provides an important insight into likely long-term genetic adaptations (<xref rid="TPW017C3" ref-type="bibr">Alberto et al. 2013</xref>).</p><p>The physiological responses to drought are complex and traits vary in their importance depending on severity, duration and timing of the drought (<xref rid="TPW017C10" ref-type="bibr">Bréda and Badeau 2008</xref>, <xref rid="TPW017C68" ref-type="bibr">Tardieu and Tuberosa 2010</xref>). These traits present as reduced leaf size and number, abscisic acid (ABA)-dependent and -independent signalling, lowered stomatal aperture and numbers, reduced stomatal conductance (<italic>g</italic><sub>s</sub>), decreased leaf growth, altered patterns of root development and improved water use efficiency (WUE) (<xref rid="TPW017C68" ref-type="bibr">Tardieu and Tuberosa 2010</xref>). Moreover, microarray studies on linkage between physiological responses and underlying regulatory genes as well as metabolic networks in response to drought are elucidated in model plant species, including poplar (<italic>Populus deltoides</italic> Marshall and <italic>Populus trichocarpa</italic> T. &amp; G. (<xref rid="TPW017C67" ref-type="bibr">Street et al. 2006</xref>), <italic>Populus euphratica</italic> Olivier (<xref rid="TPW017C9" ref-type="bibr">Bogeat-Triboulot et al. 2007</xref>), <italic>P. deltoides</italic> × <italic>Populus nigra</italic> L. (<xref rid="TPW017C17" ref-type="bibr">Cohen et al. 2010</xref>), <italic>Populus balsamifera</italic> L (<xref rid="TPW017C31" ref-type="bibr">Hamanishi et al. 2010</xref>, <xref rid="TPW017C33" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>) and <italic>P. nigra</italic> × <italic>Populus maximowiczii</italic> A. Henry (<xref rid="TPW017C81" ref-type="bibr">Wilkins et al. 2009</xref>)).</p><p>Furthermore, microarray studies on drought tolerance in <italic>P. balsamifera</italic> have identified variation in the pattern of transcript abundance between genotypes, which was correlated to growth maintenance after a water deficit (<xref rid="TPW017C31" ref-type="bibr">Hamanishi et al. 2010</xref>). These important studies generally focus on using commercial tree genotypes to elucidate gene expression changes that may be involved in determining water deficit responses. Although <italic>Populus</italic> is often defined as sensitive to drought, large variations in traits related to drought tolerance and water stress response have been reported, but generally in <italic>F</italic><sub>1</sub> or <italic>F</italic><sub>2</sub> hybrids of commercial value, and not for a wild collection such as described here. For example, osmotic adjustment varies across <italic>F</italic><sub>1</sub> and <italic>F</italic><sub>2</sub> genotypes (<xref rid="TPW017C44" ref-type="bibr">Marron et al. 2002</xref>, <xref rid="TPW017C72" ref-type="bibr">Tschaplinski et al. 2006</xref>), as does leaf expansion (<xref rid="TPW017C56" ref-type="bibr">Rae et al. 2009</xref>), leaf abscission (<xref rid="TPW017C67" ref-type="bibr">Street et al. 2006</xref>), WUE (<xref rid="TPW017C55" ref-type="bibr">Rae et al. 2004</xref>, <xref rid="TPW017C48" ref-type="bibr">Monclus et al. 2005</xref>, <xref rid="TPW017C49" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>, <xref rid="TPW017C78" ref-type="bibr">Voltas et al. 2006</xref>, <xref rid="TPW017C21" ref-type="bibr">Dillen et al. 2008</xref>) and Δ<sup>13</sup>C (<xref rid="TPW017C50" ref-type="bibr">Monclus et al. 2012</xref>). Stomatal traits linked to improved drought tolerance are complex and related to both stomatal function (opening and closing) and stomatal development and patterning. However, there is a limited understanding of genomic responses to drought in wild collections collected across a large geographical scale, which may harbour genetic potential for adaptation and increasingly provide the focus for broad geographical spanning genomic and genetic analysis of links between traits and genes. Recently, the potential to exploit natural genetic variation has been recognized in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> with genome-wide association studies for traits becoming routine (<xref rid="TPW017C6" ref-type="bibr">Atwell et al. 2010</xref>), but the relevance of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> for understanding tree adaptation may be limited (<xref rid="TPW017C69" ref-type="bibr">Taylor 2002</xref>). Drought tolerance is an obviously multigenic trait and genomic technologies allow the investigation of such traits, in contrast to traditional single gene studies that can limit the focus to the interaction between a small number of genes and, therefore, impede the identification of different pathways involved in drought response and adaptation.</p><p>European black poplar (<italic>P. nigra</italic>) is a riparian species that is widely distributed in Europe, North Africa and Central and West Asia (<xref rid="TPW017C76" ref-type="bibr">Vanden Broeck 2003</xref>). It has many economic uses, including domestic plantations and breeding programmes (<xref rid="TPW017C76" ref-type="bibr">Vanden Broeck 2003</xref>). Ecologically, <italic>P. nigra</italic> is a keystone riparian species (<xref rid="TPW017C76" ref-type="bibr">Vanden Broeck 2003</xref>), threatened by river drainage, water management (<xref rid="TPW017C28" ref-type="bibr">Gaudet et al. 2008</xref>) and climate change. Understanding phenotypic plasticity of <italic>P. nigra</italic> in response to drought is important. <italic>Populus</italic> is also widely accepted to be a model tree since it is fast growing, its genome is fully sequenced and there are a wide array of applicable genomic and genetic resources available (<xref rid="TPW017C69" ref-type="bibr">Taylor 2002</xref>, <xref rid="TPW017C73" ref-type="bibr">Tuskan et al. 2004</xref>, <xref rid="TPW017C74" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>, <xref rid="TPW017C37" ref-type="bibr">Jansson and Douglas 2007</xref>). Although poplars are considered sensitive to drought as they are abundant in riparian environments and often have a high demand for water (<xref rid="TPW017C22" ref-type="bibr">Dreyer et al. 2004</xref>, <xref rid="TPW017C67" ref-type="bibr">Street et al. 2006</xref>), considerable variation in response to water deficit has been observed between genotypes of <italic>Populus</italic> (<xref rid="TPW017C44" ref-type="bibr">Marron et al. 2002</xref>, <xref rid="TPW017C49" ref-type="bibr">Monclus et al. 2006</xref>, <xref rid="TPW017C67" ref-type="bibr">Street et al. 2006</xref>, <xref rid="TPW017C35" ref-type="bibr">Huang et al. 2009</xref>, <xref rid="TPW017C58" ref-type="bibr">Regier et al. 2009</xref>, <xref rid="TPW017C16" ref-type="bibr">Cocozza et al. 2010</xref>, <xref rid="TPW017C77" ref-type="bibr">Viger et al. 2013</xref>).</p><p>The aims of this study were (i) to quantify natural variation of productivity and other water use-associated traits in a broad, natural collection of black poplar, and examine the relationship between these traits and tree adaptation and their region of origin, which differ particularly in precipitation, (ii) to quantify phenotypic plasticity in response to drought in a group of genotypes and (iii) to determine the transcriptomic differences underlying drought tolerance in extreme genotypes from this natural collection.</p></sec><sec id="s2" disp-level="1"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="s2a" disp-level="2"><title>Common garden experiment</title><sec id="s2a1" disp-level="3"><title>Plant material and growth conditions</title><p>Cuttings of 479 genotypes of <italic>P. nigra</italic> from wild populations were collected from five different European countries, including Spain, France, Italy, Germany and The Netherlands (see <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://treephys.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/treephys/tpw017/-/DC1" ext-link-type="uri">Table S1 available as Supplementary Data at <italic>Tree Physiology</italic> Online</ext-link>). Genotypes were grouped into 11 populations related to the river system near the collection (Figure <xref rid="TPW017F1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). Hardwood cuttings were planted in a common garden in Belgium, Geraardsbergen (50°46′24″N, 3°52′56″E) in spring 2004, cut at the base in the spring of 2005 and side stems removed so that trees grew as single stems in June 2005. The experiment followed a randomized block design with six blocks each containing one replicate of each genotype with a double row of the commercial <italic>Populus</italic> genotype ‘Muur’ planted around the six blocks to minimize edge effects. The trees were planted at 0.75 × 2 m spacing. The site was rain-fed and not fertilized between March and September, but it was weed controlled and treated with fungicides every 3 weeks during these months in 2004–07.
</p><fig id="TPW017F1" position="float"><?disp-level 4?><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>Association population information and measurements from the common garden experiment in Belgium: mean annual rainfall and temperature per river population (a), map of the 11 river populations of <italic>P. nigra</italic> collected in five European countries (b), leaf size and shape variation between populations (c), leaf area in mm<sup>2</sup> (d), SI in % (e), stem circumference in cm (f) and wood carbon isotope discrimination in ‰ (g). Same letter indicates no significant difference at the 5% level, Student–Newman–Keuls post hoc testing. Each value with bars represents the average ± standard error.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="image" xlink:href="tpw01701.jpg"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/d4bd/4969554/d39007c03049/tpw01701.jpg?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?><?image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?original-height 2823?><?original-width 3940?><?scaled-height 565?><?scaled-width 788?></graphic><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="thumb" xlink:href="tpw01701.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/d4bd/4969554/721897d80eb7/tpw01701.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></alternatives></fig></sec><sec id="s2a2" disp-level="3"><title>Assessing phenotypic traits in the <italic>P. nigra</italic> collection</title><p>Each replicate was assessed for 12 morphological traits over three growing seasons (2005, 2006 and 2007). The youngest fully mature leaf was harvested, traced while fresh and placed in a paper bag. Leaf outlines were scanned using an Umax Astra 6700 scanner and assessed using ImageJ software (Image J.1.32.j, NIH, Bethesda, MD, USA). Leaf outlines were used for the measurement of leaf area, leaf length and leaf width, and calculating leaf ratio (length : width). Leaves collected in the second growing season (2005) were placed in paper bags then dried for 48 h at 80 °C, and weighed to calculate specific leaf area (SLA) as the ratio of leaf area to leaf dry weight.</p><p>Epidermal cell number and size were measured using cell imprints taken in 2006 from the first interveinal region of the abaxial surface of the first fully mature leaf following the methods of <xref rid="TPW017C27" ref-type="bibr">Gardner et al. (1995)</xref>. Images of cell imprints were assessed in ImageJ (<xref rid="TPW017C1" ref-type="bibr">Abràmoff et al. 2004</xref>) to count the number of cells and stomata per unit area and average cell area of 10 cells per leaf. Subsequently, stomatal density (ratio of stomata number per unit area), stomatal index (SI, ratio of the number of stomata per total cell number as a percentage) and cell number per leaf, estimated as the ratio of leaf area to cell area, were calculated. Height was recorded following the first year of growth (2005), and circumference 1 m above ground level was assessed following the second (2006) and third year of growth (2007).</p><p>Improved WUE is also associated with severe drought, where WUE is the ratio between net carbon assimilation (<italic>A</italic>) and transpiration rate (<italic>E</italic>), and is negatively associated with carbon isotope discrimination (Δ<sup>13</sup>C) or positively correlated with carbon isotope composition (δ<sup>13</sup>C) (<xref rid="TPW017C24" ref-type="bibr">Farquhar and Richard 1984</xref>, <xref rid="TPW017C25" ref-type="bibr">Farquhar et al. 1989</xref>, <xref rid="TPW017C18" ref-type="bibr">Condon et al. 2002</xref>). Wood was collected for Δ<sup>13</sup>C measurement in March 2007, with 30 cm sections cut from 40 cm above ground. These samples were stored in a cold room in individual plastic bags before being debarked and cut into small pieces. Samples were dried in the oven for 48 h at 80 °C before being ground using a ball grinder (Glen Creston ball, Retsch MM300, London, UK) and stored in a glass container. One milligram of material was weighed and placed into a 6 × 4 mm tin capsule (Elemental Microanalysis, Devon, UK). Samples were analysed using a SerCon 20-20 Stable Isotope Analyser with ANCA-GSL Solid/Liquid Preparation Module (SerCon, Crewe, UK). Carbon isotope composition was determined by δ<sup>13</sup>C (‰) = δ<sub>plant</sub> = [(<italic>R</italic><sub>sample</sub> − <italic>R</italic><sub>reference</sub>)/<italic>R</italic><sub>reference</sub>] × 1000, where <italic>R</italic><sub>sample</sub> and <italic>R</italic><sub>reference</sub> are the <sup>13</sup>C/<sup>12</sup>C ratios of the sample and the reference, respectively, in Vienna Pee Dee Belemnite units (<xref rid="TPW017C62" ref-type="bibr">Scrimgeour et al. 2004</xref>). Carbon isotope discrimination was calculated as Δ<sup>13</sup>C (‰) = [(δ<sub>air</sub> − δ<sub>plant</sub>)/(1 + (δ<sub>plant</sub>/1000)] with δ<sub>air</sub> assumed to be −8‰ (<xref rid="TPW017C24" ref-type="bibr">Farquhar and Richard 1984</xref>, <xref rid="TPW017C49" ref-type="bibr">Monclus et al. 2006</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec id="s2b" disp-level="2"><title>Drought experiment</title><sec id="s2b1" disp-level="3"><title>Plant material and growth conditions</title><p>In order to examine phenotypic plasticity related to water deficit, a subset of trees was chosen for a moderate drought glasshouse experiment in Southampton, UK. Six genotypes were selected from the <italic>P. nigra</italic> collection (see <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://treephys.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/treephys/tpw017/-/DC1" ext-link-type="uri">Table S2 available as Supplementary Data at <italic>Tree Physiology</italic> Online</ext-link>): four from the extreme ‘leaf size’ genotypes (two Spanish ‘small leaf’, Sp1, Sp2; one Italian ‘large leaf’, Ita; and one from the Netherlands ‘large leaf’, NL) and two from the Drôme population in France (Fr1 and Fr2). These genotypes were chosen as typical ‘small-leaf’ genotypes from arid areas. The French genotypes were selected to represent a typical leaf morphology from a broad range in temperature and precipitation patterns. Cuttings were planted in John Innes No. 2 (John Innes, Norwich, UK) without fertilization in January 2007 in a glasshouse and cut back in November 2007 at 10 cm from the base. From November 2007, the trees were watered daily and put into dormancy conditions (natural light, 15 °C : 13 °C, day : night). In May 2008, the temperature in the glasshouse was set at 22 °C : 16 °C, day : night. During the experiment, photoperiod was maintained 16 h : 8 h, light : dark with a minimum photosynthetic active radiation at the top of the plants of 150 μmol m<sup>−2</sup> s<sup>−1</sup>, supplementing natural sunlight. The number of replicates for each genotype varied between 5 and 10 plants per condition (see <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://treephys.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/treephys/tpw017/-/DC1" ext-link-type="uri">Table S2 available as Supplementary Data at <italic>Tree Physiology</italic> Online</ext-link>). The trees were randomized in 10 blocks containing one replicate per genotype per treatment.</p><p>At the beginning of the experiment on 1 September 2008, 200 ml of water was added to each potted tree and the pots were then covered in aluminium foil to prevent water evaporation. The first mature leaf and the first emerging young leaf were tagged with cotton string. From 1 September until 1 October, soil moisture content was measured every morning with a Delta-T ML2x ThetaProbe connected to an HH2 moisture meter (Delta-T Devices, Cambridge, UK). Well-watered trees (control) were watered to field capacity and drought-stressed trees were kept between 15 and 20% volume soil moisture as has been determined as a suitable moderate drought treatment for poplar (<xref rid="TPW017C67" ref-type="bibr">Street et al. 2006</xref>). Using a repeated measurements test over time, soil moisture content showed significant differences between treatment (<italic>F</italic><sub>1,50</sub> = 363.17, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001) but no significant differences between genotypes (<italic>F</italic><sub>5,50</sub> = 1.06, <italic>P</italic> = 0.392) and no genotype × treatment interaction effect (<italic>F</italic><sub>5,50</sub> = 0.82, <italic>P</italic> = 0.543), meaning all the genotypes had their soil moisture decreased equally under drought (see Figure <xref rid="TPW017F3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>, see <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://treephys.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/treephys/tpw017/-/DC1" ext-link-type="uri">Figures S1 and S2 available as Supplementary Data at <italic>Tree Physiology</italic> Online</ext-link>).</p><fig id="TPW017F3" position="float"><?disp-level 4?><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>Soil moisture content (%) over time (days after drought) for each genotype (a). Filled symbols represent well-watered (control) and open symbols are for drought treatments. Each value with bars represents the average ± standard error. Photographic representation of the morphological effects of drought on the trees grown in the greenhouse (b).</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="image" xlink:href="tpw01703.jpg"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/d4bd/4969554/d7326404fe3f/tpw01703.jpg?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?><?image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?original-height 4487?><?original-width 3237?><?scaled-height 997?><?scaled-width 719?></graphic><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="thumb" xlink:href="tpw01703.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/d4bd/4969554/289b42a2f527/tpw01703.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></alternatives></fig></sec><sec id="s2b2" disp-level="3"><title>Physiological and growth measurements</title><p>Biomass measurements were conducted on 1 September 2008 (0 day after drought (DAD)) and 17 September 2008 (16DAD). Measures included height, stem diameter measured using digital callipers at 10 cm from the stem base, the number of branches and the number of leaves. Growth was calculated as the difference between 0DAD and 16DAD for stem height and diameter, as well as number of branches and leaves. Leaves newly developed (NLN) during the experiment above the tag on the first emerging leaf were also counted at 16DAD and used with the total number of leaves at 0DAD and 16DAD to calculate the number of fallen leaves, as senescence = (NL<sub>16DAD</sub> − NL<sub>0DAD</sub>) − NLN. The third mature leaf (counting from the uppermost mature leaf) was sampled at 27DAD, traced and dried as described above. Dried leaves were used to calculate SLA, the ratio of leaf area (prior to drying) to leaf dry mass (<xref rid="TPW017C45" ref-type="bibr">Marron et al. 2005</xref>).</p><p>The first three leaves that emerged on the main stem during the experiment were followed for leaf area using the leaf tagged on 0DAD. The contour of the leaves was traced onto paper before the images were scanned and processed using ImageJ (<xref rid="TPW017C1" ref-type="bibr">Abràmoff et al. 2004</xref>). Stomatal conductance was measured on the first mature leaf tagged at 0DAD, 5DAD and 15DAD, using a steady-state porometer (LI-1600; LI-COR, Inc., Lincoln, NE, USA). In order to examine variation in WUE, a young leaf (third leaf from the top) of each tree was placed in a paper bag on 19DAD and oven dried. Δ<sup>13</sup>C was measured as described for the wood collected in Belgium.</p></sec><sec id="s2b3" disp-level="3"><title>Gene expression analysis</title><p>Young leaves were sampled on 19DAD for gene expression analyses (microarrays and real-time polymerase chain reaction (PCR)). Two genotypes—one from Spain (Sp2) and one from Italy (Ita)—were selected for microarray analysis based on being the most extreme genotypes in terms of morphology. Each sample (the first two unfurled leaves) was flash frozen in liquid nitrogen and stored at −80 °C for further analysis. RNA was extracted following the cetyl trimethlammonium bromide protocol from <xref rid="TPW017C14" ref-type="bibr">Chang et al. (1993)</xref>. Eight RNA samples, corresponding to two biological replicates of both well-watered and drought treatments per genotype, were sent to the European Arabidopsis Stock Centre (NASC, Loughborough, UK) microarray service for the cDNA synthesis, fragmentation, array hybridization and scanning using Affymetrix GeneChip Poplar Genome Arrays (Affymetrix, Santa Clara, CA, USA). Affymetrix CEL files were imported into R software (<xref rid="TPW017C57" ref-type="bibr">R Development Core Team 2014</xref>). Probe sets exhibiting no signal intensity were filtered out by a Present call procedure as described by <xref rid="TPW017C47" ref-type="bibr">McClintock and Edenberg (2006)</xref>. Briefly, CEL files were normalized using the MAS5 algorithm with default parameters (affy package, v1.48.0). MAS5 provides a detection call, Absent (A), Present (P) or Marginal (M), which indicates whether the specific transcript is detectable. For each probe set, the percentage of Present calls in each condition was calculated. Probe sets that exhibited a percentage of Present calls of 100% in at least one condition for both genotypes were kept. The other probe sets were removed from the analysis. This procedure also allowed probe sets that hybridized exclusively to one genotype to be discarded (<xref rid="TPW017C17" ref-type="bibr">Cohen et al. 2010</xref>). Finally, 31,084 validated probe sets were retained. In order to compute differential gene expression, CEL files were then normalized using the RMA algorithm with default parameters (affy package, v1.48.0). Differential expression was calculated as log<sub>2</sub>(fold change) between drought and control samples for the 31,084 validated probe sets. Statistical significance of differential expression was tested using moderated <italic>t</italic>-tests implemented in the eBayes function (limma package v3.24.12, <xref rid="TPW017C64" ref-type="bibr">Smyth 2004</xref>) and false discovery rate (FDR) corrections for multiple testing were applied. Thresholds of |log<sub>2</sub>(FC)| ≥ 1 and corrected <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05 were used to identify differentially expressed genes. Probe sets were annotated using the Poparray website (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://aspendb.uga.edu/poparray" ext-link-type="uri">http://aspendb.uga.edu/poparray</ext-link>) and assigned to a <italic>Populus</italic> gene model (v. 3.0) and its closest <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> homologue, and gene ontology (GO) biological process, cellular component and molecular function classifications.</p><p>The software MapMan (<xref rid="TPW017C70" ref-type="bibr">Thimm et al. 2004</xref>) was used for pathway analysis. Statistics (Wilcoxon Rank Sum Test with a Benjamini–Hochberg FDR correction) were implemented in MapMan to reveal BINs (groups of functionally similar items—genes, enzyme activities, metabolites, used to construct pathways) exhibiting a significant difference in expression profile behaviour compared with the other BINs. Gene ontology enrichment was also studied using the parametric analysis of gene set enrichment (PAGE) tool on the AgriGo website (<xref rid="TPW017C23" ref-type="bibr">Du et al. 2010</xref>) with default parameters using validated probe sets as the reference.</p><p>Results of the microarray experiment were confirmed using quantitative real-time PCR (qPCR) for a set of differentially expressed candidate genes. Forward and reverse primers were designed, from the <italic>P. trichocarpa</italic> genome (v1.2), specifically to each gene (see <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://treephys.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/treephys/tpw017/-/DC1" ext-link-type="uri">Table S3 available as Supplementary Data at <italic>Tree Physiology</italic> Online</ext-link>). Reverse transcription of RNA to cDNA was performed using the ImProm-II Reverse Transcription kit (Promega UK, Southampton, UK) following the manufacturer’s instructions. Each qPCR was composed of 5 µL 2× Precision-SY Master Mix (PrimerDesign Ltd, Southampton, UK), 5 pmol forward and reverse primers and 25 ng diluted cDNA. Plates were run on a Chrom4 Real-Time PCR Detection System (Bio-Rad Laboratories, Hercules, CA, USA). Reactions were incubated at 95 °C for 10 min and then 40 cycles of 15 s at 95 °C, 1 min at 60 °C and a plate read, followed by an incubation at 72 °C for 10 min. A melting curve was then performed from 60 to 95 °C with a read every 0.2 °C and 1 s hold, in order to check for primer dimers, DNA contamination and secondary products. Values were exported with the software Opticon Monitor 3.1 (Bio-Rad Laboratories). Amplification efficiency was measured following the equation from <xref rid="TPW017C42" ref-type="bibr">Liu and Saint (2002)</xref>:
</p><disp-formula id="TPW017UM1"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="DmEquation1" display="block" overflow="scroll"><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mfenced open="(" close=")"><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">A</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">B</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mo>/</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">A</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">B</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:math></disp-formula><p>
where <italic>R</italic><sub>n,A</sub> and <italic>R</italic><sub>n,B</sub> are <italic>R</italic><sub>n</sub> at arbitrary thresholds A and B in an individual curve, respectively, and <italic>C</italic><sub>T,A</sub> and <italic>C</italic><sub>T,B</sub> are the threshold cycles at these arbitrary thresholds (<xref rid="TPW017C42" ref-type="bibr">Liu and Saint 2002</xref>).</p><p>Ratios were calculated as:
</p><disp-formula id="TPW017UM2"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="DmEquation2" display="block" overflow="scroll"><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="thickmathspace"/><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">control</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">drought</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="thickmathspace"/><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">target</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="thickmathspace"/><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">control</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">drought</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="thickmathspace"/><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">reference</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:math></disp-formula></sec><sec id="s2b4" disp-level="3"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>Data from the Belgium common garden experiment were analysed using the SPSS software package (SPSS, Chicago, IL, USA). Kolmogorov–Smirnov tests were used to test for normality, and transformation (log<sub>10</sub>) was carried out when required. A general linear model (GLM) tested the effects of block and river population:
</p><disp-formula id="TPW017UM3"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="DmEquation3" display="block" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>ϵ</mml:mi></mml:math></disp-formula><p>
where μ is the mean, <italic>Y<sub>ij</sub></italic> is the phenotype in the <italic>i</italic>th block and in the <italic>j</italic>th river population, α<italic><sub>i</sub></italic> is the block effect, β<italic><sub>j</sub></italic> is the river population effect and ϵ is the residual error. A comparison of means was carried out between river populations using a Student–Newman–Keuls post hoc test.</p><p>A GLM was also performed to test genotype effects:
</p><disp-formula id="TPW017UM4"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="DmEquation4" display="block" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>ϵ</mml:mi></mml:math></disp-formula><p>
where <italic>Y<sub>i</sub></italic> is the phenotype in the <italic>i</italic>th genotype, α<italic><sub>i</sub></italic> is the genotype effect and ϵ is the residual error.</p><p>Climatic data from the region of origin for genotypes were correlated with and among phenotypic traits as measured in the common garden was tested using Spearman’s ρ in SPSS v19.0 (SPSS).</p><p>Data from the glasshouse experiment were also analysed for genotype and treatment effect (and their interaction) using the SPSS software package (SPSS). Normality (Kolmogorov–Smirnov test) and block effects were checked before performing an analysis of variance (ANOVA) GLM. Data were transformed using a natural log when required. A GLM tested the effects of genotype and treatment:
</p><disp-formula id="TPW017UM5"><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="DmEquation5" display="block" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>Y</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>μ</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>α</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>β</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>ϵ</mml:mi></mml:math></disp-formula><p>
where <italic>Y<sub>ij</sub></italic> is the phenotype in the <italic>i</italic>th genotype and in the <italic>j</italic>th treatment, α<italic><sub>i</sub></italic> is the genotype effect, β<italic><sub>j</sub></italic> is the treatment effect and ϵ is the residual error. A comparison of means was carried out among genotypes using a Student–Newman–Keuls post hoc test. A test for repeated measurements was used for leaf area over time for each leaf number. Phenotypic plasticity in drought response was quantified using the equation <inline-formula><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="ImEquation1" overflow="scroll"><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">drought</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">control</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>/</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">control</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo><mml:mo>×</mml:mo><mml:mn>100</mml:mn><mml:mspace width="thickmathspace"/></mml:math></inline-formula> from <xref rid="TPW017C67" ref-type="bibr">Street et al. (2006)</xref>.</p></sec></sec></sec><sec id="s3" disp-level="1"><title>Results</title><sec id="s3a" disp-level="2"><title>Common garden experiment</title><p>The collection of nearly 500 genotypes of <italic>P. nigra</italic> selected from contrasting climatic zones across Europe was used to study natural variation in wood carbon isotope discrimination (Δ<sup>13</sup>C), leaf, cell and biomass traits for trees grown under well-watered conditions in a Belgian common garden field site (Figure <xref rid="TPW017F1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). Significant differences in plant morphology were observed between natural populations. Leaf area, stem circumference and Δ<sup>13</sup>C varied significantly between river sites (<italic>F</italic><sub>10,482</sub> = 129.8, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001; <italic>F</italic><sub>10,453</sub> = 35.2, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001; <italic>F</italic><sub>10,466</sub> = 33.5, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001, respectively, with Type III sums of squares). For SI, although the difference was not significant (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05), a trend was apparent with northern populations (Italy, The Netherlands and Germany) exhibiting a high SI, while genotypes from French populations showed a lower SI. In contrast to other measurements, the Spanish genotypes were intermediate in their ranking (Figure <xref rid="TPW017F1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>e). Leaf area and stem circumference were highest in the northern river populations (Italy, The Netherlands and Germany), while Spanish and southern French genotypes had the smallest leaves and stem circumference (Figure <xref rid="TPW017F1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>d and f). Δ<sup>13</sup>C tended to decrease along this north–south latitudinal gradient, although there were exceptions, such as for genotypes from west Loire (Figure <xref rid="TPW017F1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>g), but suggests that, under well-watered conditions, WUE was higher for genotypes from northern latitudes, when grown in the Belgian common garden.</p><p>Correlation between leaf, cell and biomass traits within and among growing seasons showed that leaf area correlated with tree height and circumference, both of which are woody biomass traits (see <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://treephys.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/treephys/tpw017/-/DC1" ext-link-type="uri">Table S4 available as Supplementary Data at <italic>Tree Physiology</italic> Online</ext-link>, Figure <xref rid="TPW017F2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). In the third year of growth (2006), when leaf cell traits were measured, there was a strong positive correlation between cell number per leaf and leaf area (see <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://treephys.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/treephys/tpw017/-/DC1" ext-link-type="uri">Table S4 available as Supplementary Data at <italic>Tree Physiology</italic> Online</ext-link>, Figure <xref rid="TPW017F2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>, <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.927, <italic>P </italic>&lt; 0.0001) but a weak negative correlation between cell area and leaf area (see <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://treephys.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/treephys/tpw017/-/DC1" ext-link-type="uri">Table S4 available as Supplementary Data at <italic>Tree Physiology</italic> Online</ext-link>, Figure <xref rid="TPW017F2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>, <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> = −0.235, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.0001). Furthermore, stomatal patterning correlated strongly with all biomass traits with the exception of SI, which showed no relationship with leaf shape ratios in either 2005 or 2006 (<italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> = −0.059, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.85; <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.025, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.429, respectively). Precipitation at the genotype site of origin correlated with leaf and stem phenotypic traits with higher precipitation (mean annual, minimum and maximum) correlated with increased leaf areas, which are made up of a greater number of smaller cells per leaf with more stomata, higher SLA and increased stem height and circumference (see <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://treephys.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/treephys/tpw017/-/DC1" ext-link-type="uri">Table S4 available as Supplementary Data at <italic>Tree Physiology</italic> Online</ext-link>). Additionally, higher temperatures (mean annual, minimum and maximum) correlated with leaf shape ratio and SLA. The temperature of the coolest month seems most important with respect to leaf area and cell number per leaf, as well as stem height and circumference in 2005 and 2006, respectively. However, mean annual temperature and the temperature of the warmest month also correlated with reduced leaf cell size and stem circumference and increased abaxial stomatal density (see <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://treephys.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/treephys/tpw017/-/DC1" ext-link-type="uri">Table S4 available as Supplementary Data at <italic>Tree Physiology</italic> Online</ext-link>).
</p><fig id="TPW017F2" position="float"><?disp-level 3?><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>Correlations of biomass traits of interest: leaf area and height in 2005 (a), leaf area and cell area in 2006 (b) and leaf area and cell number per leaf in 2006 (c). Leaf traits are based on the youngest fully mature leaf from each tree. Spearman’s rho (<italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup>
<sub>s</sub>) and the probability that it differs from zero (<italic>P</italic>) are provided for each correlation.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="image" xlink:href="tpw01702.jpg"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/d4bd/4969554/ce3bca7af00d/tpw01702.jpg?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?><?image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?original-height 4615?><?original-width 2710?><?scaled-height 1318?><?scaled-width 774?></graphic><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="thumb" xlink:href="tpw01702.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/d4bd/4969554/a75c8ed8817c/tpw01702.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></alternatives></fig></sec><sec id="s3b" disp-level="2"><title>Drought experiment</title><p>Six contrasting genotypes were selected from the common garden trial to further elucidate phenotypic plasticity in response to drought, and how this varied across genotypes adapted to local drought conditions. These genotypes were subjected to a moderate drought in a controlled environment glasshouse in southern England (Figure <xref rid="TPW017F3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>a). Variation in response to drought was observed across the six selected genotypes (Table <xref rid="TPW017TB1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). Interaction between genotype and treatment was significant for Δ<sup>13</sup>C, from a two-way ANOVA, and close to significant (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.10) for stem growth. Five of the nine traits measured showed both genotype and drought main ANOVA effects, while highly significant drought effects were observed for <italic>g</italic><sub>s</sub>, Δ<sup>13</sup>C, leaf production and growth traits (Table <xref rid="TPW017TB1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). Furthermore, SLA varied significantly between genotypes but was unaffected by the drought treatment (Table <xref rid="TPW017TB1" ref-type="table">1</xref>).

</p><table-wrap id="TPW017TB1" position="float"><?disp-level 3?><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>Summary of statistical results presenting the <italic>F</italic>-value and <italic>P</italic>-value for each trait using a GLM test for the main effects genotype and treatment and the interaction genotype × treatment. Bold values are significant (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05).</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Trait</th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Genotype<hr/>
</th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Water treatment<hr/>
</th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Genotype × water treatment<hr/>
</th></tr><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>F</italic></th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P</italic>-value</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>F</italic></th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P</italic>-value</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>F</italic></th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P</italic>-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>g</italic><sub>s</sub> 5DAD</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.078</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&lt;0.001</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.860</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&lt;0.001</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.344</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.252</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>g</italic><sub>s</sub> 15DAD</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.469</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.207</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">103.092</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&lt;0.001</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.912</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.100</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Δ<sup>13</sup>C</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.893</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&lt;0.001</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.511</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.008</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.567</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.037</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Height growth</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.579</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&lt;0.001</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.086</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&lt;0.001</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.726</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.606</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stem diameter growth</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.116</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.071</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.77</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&lt;0.001</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.989</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.088</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Branches formation</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.697</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.627</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.948</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.333</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.639</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.670</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">New leaf development</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.216</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&lt;0.001</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.964</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&lt;0.001</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.523</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.758</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Leaf senescence</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.502</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.036</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.182</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.025</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.839</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.526</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SLA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.538</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>&lt;0.001</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.977</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.088</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.923</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.470</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><sec id="s3b1" disp-level="3"><title>Biomass</title><p>Images taken on 20DAD revealed the main morphological variation in response to drought across the six selected genotypes (represented by four genotypes in Figure <xref rid="TPW017F3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>b). Biomass production was also measured (see <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://treephys.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/treephys/tpw017/-/DC1" ext-link-type="uri">Table S5 available as Supplementary Data at <italic>Tree Physiology</italic> Online</ext-link>, Figure <xref rid="TPW017F4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>) and revealed that height growth decreased for all genotypes in response to drought (genotype: <italic>F</italic><sub>5,85</sub> = 6.6, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001; treatment: <italic>F</italic><sub>1,85</sub> = 37.1, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001) with the largest decrease (−86%) for the Ita genotype (Figure <xref rid="TPW017F4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>a). Fr1 and Sp2 maintained some height growth under drought with only moderate reductions apparent (−32 and −37%, respectively).
</p><fig id="TPW017F4" position="float"><?disp-level 4?><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><p>Percentage difference of biomass using the formula [(drought − control)/(control × 100)] from <xref rid="TPW017C67" ref-type="bibr">Street et al. (2006)</xref>: height growth in mm (a), stem diameter growth in mm (b), new leaf formation (c), leaf senescence (d), branch formation (e), SLA in cm<sup>2</sup> g<sup>−1</sup> (f), <italic>g</italic><sub>s</sub> in μmol m<sup>−2</sup> s<sup>−1</sup> at 5 DAD (g) and 15 DAD (h), and carbon isotope discrimination in ‰ (i).</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="image" xlink:href="tpw01704.jpg"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/d4bd/4969554/b29918a87a73/tpw01704.jpg?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?><?image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?original-height 3987?><?original-width 3704?><?scaled-height 797?><?scaled-width 740?></graphic><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="thumb" xlink:href="tpw01704.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/d4bd/4969554/1a8d914dc467/tpw01704.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></alternatives></fig><p>Differences between genotypes were apparent for both leaf production (formation) and leaf loss (senescence). Leaf production differed significantly between genotypes (<italic>F</italic><sub>5,91</sub> = 16.2, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001). In addition, leaf production was significantly affected by drought, particularly in Ita, Fr2 and NL (<italic>F</italic><sub>1,91</sub> = 25.0, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001, Figure <xref rid="TPW017F4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>c). One Spanish genotype (Sp2) continued to develop approximately the same number of new leaves during exposure to drought (an average of 6.0 leaves)—similar to that in well-watered conditions (6.8 leaves). In the well-watered treatment, Sp1 developed the most new leaves during the experiment (8.88), while trees from Italy only formed an average of 3.89 new leaves. Leaf senescence and loss on the main stem increased significantly under drought (<italic>F</italic><sub>1,86</sub> = 5.2, <italic>P</italic> = 0.025), but significant genotype effects were also apparent (<italic>F</italic><sub>5,86</sub> = 2.5, <italic>P</italic> = 0.036). French and Spanish genotypes lost more leaves (Figure <xref rid="TPW017F4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>d), while trees from Italy and the Netherlands largely retained leaves. Sp2 also developed two to four more branches on average in drought compared with well-watered conditions (Figure <xref rid="TPW017F4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>e). However, this trait did not show any significant genotype (<italic>F</italic><sub>5,81</sub> = 0.697, <italic>P</italic> = 0.627) or treatment (<italic>F</italic><sub>1,81</sub> = 0.948, <italic>P</italic> = 0.33) effects. Genotypes NL, Ita and Fr2 developed no branches in response to water deficit. Specific leaf area was measured at the end of the experiment and revealed a significant genotype (<italic>F</italic><sub>5,87</sub> = 10.5, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001) but not a treatment effect (<italic>F</italic><sub>1,87</sub> = 3.0, <italic>P</italic> = 0.09).</p></sec><sec id="s3b2" disp-level="3"><title>Stomatal conductance and carbon isotope discrimination</title><p>Stomatal conductance was measured during the progression of drought (see <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://treephys.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/treephys/tpw017/-/DC1" ext-link-type="uri">Table S5 available as Supplementary Data at <italic>Tree Physiology</italic> Online</ext-link>, Figure <xref rid="TPW017F4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>g and h). Early after the onset of drought (5DAD, Figure <xref rid="TPW017F4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>g), Spanish and French genotypes reacted quickly to water deficit with <italic>g</italic><sub>s</sub> declining rapidly by −54 and −36%, respectively (genotype: <italic>F</italic><sub>5,96</sub> = 5.1, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001, treatment: <italic>F</italic><sub>1,96</sub> = 15.9, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001). In contrast, the Ita genotype showed a small increase in <italic>g</italic><sub>s</sub> in response to drought (3.4%) and NL a moderate decline (−17%). After 15 days of drought (Figure <xref rid="TPW017F4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>h), these contrasting early responses of stomata to drought were no longer apparent and all genotypes showed a significant decline in <italic>g</italic><sub>s</sub> (<italic>F</italic><sub>1,92</sub> = 103.1, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001). Young leaves developed during the experiment were collected to measure Δ<sup>13</sup>C (Figure <xref rid="TPW017F4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>i). Δ<sup>13</sup>C showed significant variation between genotypes (<italic>F</italic><sub>5,58</sub> = 5.9, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001), a highly significant effect of drought (<italic>F</italic><sub>1,58</sub> = 7.5, <italic>P</italic> = 0.008) and a significant interaction of genotype × treatment (<italic>F</italic><sub>5,58</sub> = 2.6, <italic>P</italic> = 0.037), indicating that the response to drought differed depending on genotype. While Sp1, Sp2 and Fr1 decreased their Δ<sup>13</sup>C by ∼10% during the drought treatment, possibly indicating an increase in WUE, Fr2 showed no variation between treatment and Ita increased Δ<sup>13</sup>C under drought.</p></sec><sec id="s3b3" disp-level="3"><title>Leaf growth</title><p>Leaf area was measured for the first three leaves emerging from 1 to 19DAD (Figure <xref rid="TPW017F5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>). Genotype had a significant effect on leaf area for all leaf numbers (Leaf 1: <italic>F</italic><sub>5,82</sub> = 7.538, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001; Leaf 2: <italic>F</italic><sub>5,54</sub> = 6.162, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001; Leaf 3: <italic>F</italic><sub>5,36</sub> = 6.328, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001). The effect of treatment was also significant (Leaf 1: <italic>F</italic><sub>1,82</sub> = 21.75, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001; Leaf 2: <italic>F</italic><sub>1,54</sub> = 26.86, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001; Leaf 3: <italic>F</italic><sub>1,36</sub> = 23.69, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001), but genotype and treatment did not interact. For the trees under well-watered conditions, both Spanish genotypes had the smallest leaves (1700 and 1000 mm<sup>2</sup> on average, respectively) and the Italian had the largest leaves (4700 mm<sup>2</sup> on average for Leaf 1). This rank order and size distribution was consistent with that observed in the common garden experiment, indicating that the greenhouse conditions did not change the phenotypic differences in these plants. Sp2 showed the smallest reduction in leaf area (−21.2%) and Fr2 the largest reduction (−66.3%) in response to drought.
</p><fig id="TPW017F5" position="float"><?disp-level 4?><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><p>Leaf area development over time (days after drought) for the first emerging leaf (square), the second leaf emerging (circle) and the third leaf emerging (triangle) under well-watered conditions (solid lines and open symbols) and drought stress (broken lines and filled symbols) for each genotypes: Sp1 (a), Sp2 (b), Fr1 (c), Fr2 (d), Ita (e) and NL (f). Percentage difference in leaf area corresponds to the first emerging leaf after 18 DAD following the formula [(drought − control)/(control × 100)] from <xref rid="TPW017C67" ref-type="bibr">Street et al. (2006)</xref>.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="image" xlink:href="tpw01705.jpg"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/d4bd/4969554/2a97665c22ce/tpw01705.jpg?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?><?image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?original-height 4486?><?original-width 3210?><?scaled-height 996?><?scaled-width 713?></graphic><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="thumb" xlink:href="tpw01705.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/d4bd/4969554/51a051f9e46e/tpw01705.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></alternatives></fig></sec><sec id="s3b4" disp-level="3"><title>Transcriptome response to drought</title><p>Dramatic differences were apparent in the transcriptomic responses to drought in the contrasting Spanish and Italian genotypes selected for gene expression analysis (see <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://treephys.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/treephys/tpw017/-/DC1" ext-link-type="uri">Table S9 available as Supplementary Data at <italic>Tree Physiology</italic> Online</ext-link>). In the northern Italian genotype (Ita), 8857 probe sets displayed a significant twofold change in intensity in response to drought (3610 up-regulations and 5247 down-regulations, Figure <xref rid="TPW017F6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>a and b). In contrast, for the Spanish genotype (Sp2), only 1067 probe sets exhibited a twofold differential expression between control and drought conditions (338 up-regulations and 729 down-regulations, Figure <xref rid="TPW017F6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>a and b). Only 258 probe sets were commonly up-regulated between the two genotypes under drought and 643 were commonly down-regulated in response to drought (Figure <xref rid="TPW017F6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>c, see <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://treephys.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/treephys/tpw017/-/DC1" ext-link-type="uri">Table S9 available as Supplementary Data at <italic>Tree Physiology</italic> Online</ext-link>).
</p><fig id="TPW017F6" position="float"><?disp-level 4?><label>Figure 6.</label><caption><p>Venn diagram representing the Affymetrix ID probe sets that were twofold up-regulated (a) and down-regulated (b) in response to moderate drought—differentially expressed between the Spanish Sp2 (white) and the Italian Ita (grey) genotypes. Numbers in the circle overlap indicate the number of transcripts common to both genotypes and numbers outside the overlap indicate the number of transcripts exclusive to the genotype indicated. Circles (c) indicate the number of transcripts up-regulated and down-regulated in Sp2 compared with Ita in well-watered conditions.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="image" xlink:href="tpw01706.jpg"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/d4bd/4969554/ab7235b426b0/tpw01706.jpg?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?><?image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?original-height 2483?><?original-width 1884?><?scaled-height 992?><?scaled-width 753?></graphic><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="thumb" xlink:href="tpw01706.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/d4bd/4969554/2a863ee85253/tpw01706.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></alternatives></fig><p>A combination of pathway analysis from MapMan and PAGE analysis from AgriGO allowed functional enrichments to be identified (Table <xref rid="TPW017TB2" ref-type="table">2</xref>, Figure <xref rid="TPW017F7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>). Only three BINs were significant in the MapMan analysis for the Spanish genotype in response to drought (Table <xref rid="TPW017TB2" ref-type="table">2</xref>, see <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://treephys.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/treephys/tpw017/-/DC1" ext-link-type="uri">Table S7 available as Supplementary Data at <italic>Tree Physiology</italic> Online</ext-link> for full details): cell (<italic>P</italic> = 0.0000003), secondary metabolism (<italic>P</italic> = 0.01) and transport (<italic>P</italic> = 0.000062). The Italian genotype had 24 MapMan BINs that were significant (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05) including DNA, RNA, cell, stress, transport, hormone metabolism and signalling (Table <xref rid="TPW017TB2" ref-type="table">2</xref>, see <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://treephys.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/treephys/tpw017/-/DC1" ext-link-type="uri">Table S7 available as Supplementary Data at <italic>Tree Physiology</italic> Online</ext-link> for full details).

</p><table-wrap id="TPW017TB2" position="float"><?disp-level 4?><label>Table 2.</label><caption><p>Description of the significant BINs from the microarray transcripts list in response to drought for the Spanish and the Italian genotypes. The probability (<italic>P</italic>-value) was calculated using a Wilcoxon Rank Sum test with a Benjamini–Hochberg correction in MapMan (<xref rid="TPW017C70" ref-type="bibr">Thimm et al. 2004</xref>). Examples of significant transcripts are given for several significant BINs with the probe set ID, Poplar gene model, a brief description and log<sub>2</sub>. The complete list is in <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://treephys.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/treephys/tpw017/-/DC1" ext-link-type="uri">Table S7 available as Supplementary Data at <italic>Tree Physiology</italic> Online</ext-link>.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Genotype</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BIN code</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BIN name</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Probe set ID</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Poplar gene model</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Arabidopsis</italic> gene model</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Brief description</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Log<sub>2</sub> (FC)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ita</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DNA (128 probes, <italic>P</italic> = 7.87E-15)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DNA synthesis/chromatin structure</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ptpaffx.200289.1.s1_at</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Potri.001G074000</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AT5G44635.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Minichromosome maintenance (MCM2/3/5) family protein</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−4.97</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.1.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DNA synthesis/chromatin structure histone</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ptp.4194.1.s1_x_at</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Potri.017G123700</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AT3G45980.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Histone superfamily protein</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.62</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">DNA repair</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ptp.1405.1.s1_at</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Potri.014G128500</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AT2G47590.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Photolyase/blue-light receptor 2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.48</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ita</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cell (213 probes, <italic>P</italic> = 9.91E-18)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cell division</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ptpaffx.204723.1.s1_at</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Potri.009G089200</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AT3G19590.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Transducin/WD40 repeat-like superfamily protein</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−4.20</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cell cycle</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ptpaffx.200879.1.s1_at</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Potri.001G272000</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AT2G26760.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cyclin B1;4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−4.69</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cell vesicle transport</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ptpaffx.2864.2.s1_at</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Potri.003G177700</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AT1G04760.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vesicle-associated membrane protein 726</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.80</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ita</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stress (148 probes, <italic>P</italic> = 0.004)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stress biotic</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ptp.6055.1.s1_at</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Potri.007G043500</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AT4G37000.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Accelerated cell death 2 (ACD2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.65</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.2.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stress abiotic heat</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ptpaffx.210289.1.s1_at</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Potri.012G017600</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AT5G42020.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Heat shock protein 70 (Hsp 70) family protein</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.38</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.2.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stress abiotic drought/salt</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ptpaffx.208807.1.s1_x_at</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Potri.010G094100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AT1G26850.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>S</italic>-adenosyl-<sc>l</sc>-methionine-dependent methyltransferases superfamily protein</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.83</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ita</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">RNA (559 probes, <italic>P</italic> = 0.04)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.3.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">RNA regulation of transcription AP2/EREBP, APETALA2/ethylene-responsive element binding protein family</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ptpaffx.211416.1.s1_at</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Potri.014G008100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AT4G37750.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ANT, integrase-type DNA-binding superfamily protein</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−3.23</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.3.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">RNA regulation of transcription basic helix–loop–helix (bHLH)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ptpaffx.210224.1.s1_at</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Potri.012G031800</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AT5G53210.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">SPCH, bHLH DNA-binding superfamily protein</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−2.70</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.3.22</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">RNA regulation of transcription HB transcription factor family</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ptpaffx.38907.1.s1_at</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Potri.011G098300</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AT2G34710.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PHB, Homeobox-leucine zipper family protein/lipid-binding START domain-containing protein</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−2.21</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.3.25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">RNA regulation of transcription MYB domain transcription factor family</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ptpaffx.212699.1.s1_at</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Potri.015G041100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AT1G22640.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">myb domain protein 3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.61</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.3.32</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">RNA regulation of transcription WRKY domain transcription factor family</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ptpaffx.203170.1.s1_at</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Potri.003G111900</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AT2G30590.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">WRKY DNA-binding protein 21</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.06</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.3.50</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">RNA regulation of transcription General Transcription</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ptpaffx.200328.1.s1_s_at</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Potri.001G082700</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AT4G24150.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Growth-regulating factor 8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−2.42</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sp2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cell (57 probes, <italic>P</italic> = 3.34E-7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cell organization</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ptpaffx.148282.1.s1_s_at</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Potri.002G111900</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AT1G50010.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tubulin α-2 chain</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.52</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cell division</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ptpaffx.212842.1.s1_at</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Potri.015G090600</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AT3G25100.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cell division cycle 45</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.41</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cell cycle</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ptpaffx.63679.1.a1_s_at</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Potri.005G181400</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AT1G44110.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cyclin A1;1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−2.56</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><fig id="TPW017F7" position="float"><?disp-level 4?><label>Figure 7.</label><caption><p><italic>Z</italic>-score values of the main groups for Sp2 and Ita genotype transcripts in response to drought using the PAGE analysis from AgriGO (<xref rid="TPW017C23" ref-type="bibr">Du et al. 2010</xref>). Full analysis is in <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://treephys.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/treephys/tpw017/-/DC1" ext-link-type="uri">Table S9 available as Supplementary Data at <italic>Tree Physiology</italic> Online</ext-link>.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="image" xlink:href="tpw01707.jpg"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/d4bd/4969554/c470460037b6/tpw01707.jpg?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?><?image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?original-height 2243?><?original-width 3922?><?scaled-height 448?><?scaled-width 784?></graphic><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="thumb" xlink:href="tpw01707.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/d4bd/4969554/57b2cc0b0f11/tpw01707.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></alternatives></fig><p>Parametric analysis of gene set enrichment analysis of drought-responsive genes confirmed the results from MapMan and allowed 453 and 115 significantly enriched GO terms to be highlighted for Ita and Sp2, respectively (see <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://treephys.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/treephys/tpw017/-/DC1" ext-link-type="uri">Table S8 available as Supplementary Data at <italic>Tree Physiology</italic> Online</ext-link>). Eighty-three GO terms were commonly enriched for both genotypes. Among the 31 common down-regulated biological processes (see <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://treephys.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/treephys/tpw017/-/DC1" ext-link-type="uri">Table S8 available as Supplementary Data at <italic>Tree Physiology</italic> Online</ext-link>), 50% were related to cell division (e.g., ‘mitosis’, ‘DNA metabolic process’, ‘chromosome organization’ and ‘cell cycle’). Other negatively regulated processes were also found such as ‘regulation of gene expression’ and ‘secondary metabolic process’. Additionally, GO analysis revealed enrichment of up-regulated biological processes related to transport (GO:0006810, GO:0006812 and GO:0006811), response to stress and stimuli (GO:0006950, GO:0042221, GO:0050896 and GO:0009628) and carbohydrate catabolism (GO:0016052, GO:0019320, GO:0006007, GO:0046365 and GO:0006090) for both Ita and Sp2 (Figure <xref rid="TPW017F7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>, see <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://treephys.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/treephys/tpw017/-/DC1" ext-link-type="uri">Table S8 available as Supplementary Data at <italic>Tree Physiology</italic> Online</ext-link>). For the Spanish genotype only, functional enrichment was detected for repressed processes such as phenylpropanoid and flavonoid biosynthesis, and for induced ones involved in nucleotide and lipid metabolisms. Among the 247 biological processes enriched specifically for Ita, 135 are up-regulated including GO terms assigned to response to hormone (ABA, auxin, cytokinin, salicylic acid and jasmonate), response to abiotic and biotic stress (e.g., ‘response to water deprivation’, ‘response to osmotic stress’, ‘response to oxidative stress’ and ‘response to biotic stimulus’), metabolism and catabolism of amino acid, and to transport (ion, carbohydrate peptide, etc.). Finally, 112 down-regulated biological processes were found to be enriched for Ita only and are predominantly related to growth, development, cell division and morphogenesis. Among these down-regulated developmental processes, of particular interest were ‘stomatal complex development’ and its parent term ‘organ development’, which encompassed drought-responsive genes. Among drought-responsive genes, of particular interest were those related to stomatal development and patterning (Figure <xref rid="TPW017F8" ref-type="fig">8</xref>) and leaf development (Table <xref rid="TPW017TB3" ref-type="table">3</xref>), since these showed marked differences between genotypes in response to drought. In Sp2, only four genes were significantly down-regulated in response to drought: two <italic>ERECTA</italic> genes (<italic>ERECTA</italic>), one <italic>Erecta-like</italic> coding gene (<italic>ERL2</italic>) and <italic>MUTE</italic>, an orthologue of <italic>SPEECHLESS</italic>, which did not lead to a functional enrichment. In contrast, eight transcripts determining stomatal patterning were down-regulated in Ita in response to drought, including two <italic>SPEECHLESS</italic> orthologues (<italic>SPEECHLESS</italic> and <italic>MUTE</italic>), two (<italic>ERECTA</italic>) coding genes (<italic>ERECTA</italic>), three <italic>Erecta-like</italic> coding genes (<italic>ERL1</italic>, <italic>ERL2</italic> and <italic>ERL3</italic>) and <italic>TOO MANY MOUTHS</italic> (<italic>TMM</italic>). Transcripts controlling the activity of the shoot apical meristem and leaf development were also down-regulated in the Italian genotype in response to drought (Table <xref rid="TPW017TB3" ref-type="table">3</xref>), such as five close homologues of <italic>ASYMMETRIC LEAVES</italic> coding genes (<italic>AS1</italic>: <italic>Potri.017G112300</italic>, <italic>Potri.006G085900</italic>, <italic>Potri.004G102600</italic> and <italic>AS2</italic>: <italic>Potri. 010G177100</italic>, <italic>Potri.008G079800</italic>), six homologues of <italic>PHABULOSA</italic> (<italic>PHB</italic>), <italic>CLAVATA1</italic> (<italic>CLV1</italic>) and five homologues of <italic>AINTGUMENTA</italic> (<italic>ANT</italic>). Two of the same homologues of <italic>AS1</italic> and <italic>AS2</italic> were down-regulated in Sp2, as well as in one of the <italic>PHB</italic> homologues, but in general, as for stomatal patterning transcripts, there were far fewer changes in Sp2 then in Ita for leaf development transcript response to drought.

</p><fig id="TPW017F8" position="float"><?disp-level 4?><label>Figure 8.</label><caption><p>Gene expression changes for Sp2 and Ita in response to water deficit for stomatal patterning candidate genes: <italic>ERECTA</italic>, <italic>ERL1</italic>, <italic>ERL2</italic>, <italic>ERL3</italic>, <italic>TMM</italic>, <italic>SPCH</italic> and <italic>MUTE</italic>. Values are in log<sub>2</sub>.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="image" xlink:href="tpw01708.jpg"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/d4bd/4969554/9b9bea8ddb97/tpw01708.jpg?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?><?image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?original-height 3087?><?original-width 3882?><?scaled-height 617?><?scaled-width 776?></graphic><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="thumb" xlink:href="tpw01708.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/d4bd/4969554/0c8922c38f85/tpw01708.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></alternatives></fig><table-wrap id="TPW017TB3" position="float"><?disp-level 4?><label>Table 3.</label><caption><p>Candidate genes involved in leaf development differentially expressed under drought in the Italian (Ita) and Spanish (Sp2) genotypes. Details include the name of the gene and probe set ID, the poplar (v3.0) and <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> gene models, the log<sub>2</sub> expression ratio for each genotype (in bold if <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05) and a brief description of its function.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Name</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Probe set ID</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Poplar gene model (v3.0)</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Arabidopsis</italic> gene model</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ita log<sub>2</sub>(FC)</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sp2 log<sub>2</sub>(FC)</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Description</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>AS1</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PtpAffx.163978.1.S1_at</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Potri.004G102600</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AT2G37630.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>−2.70</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.87</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Involved in specification of the leaf proximodistal axis</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>AS1</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PtpAffx.2947.1.S1_at</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Potri.017G112300</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AT2G37630.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>−2.92</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.24</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Involved in specification of the leaf proximodistal axis</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>AS1</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PtpAffx.2947.2.A1_at</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>−1.66</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.31</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>AS1</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ptp.4356.1.S1_at</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Potri.006G085900</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AT2G37630.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>−4.93</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.92</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Involved in specification of the leaf proximodistal axis</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>AS2</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PtpAffx.207814.1.S1_at</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Potri.008G079800</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AT1G65620.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>−2.91</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−2.20</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Required for formation of a symmetric flat leaf lamina</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>AS2</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PtpAffx.209221.1.S1_at</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Potri.010G177100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AT1G65620.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>−1.82</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.23</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Required for formation of a symmetric flat leaf lamina</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>AS2</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PtpAffx.44821.1.A1_s_at</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>−2.07</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.04</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>CLV1</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PtpAffx.201597.1.S1_at</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Potri.002G019900</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AT1G75820.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>−2.06</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.52</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Controls shoot and floral meristem size</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>PHB</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ptp.548.1.S1_at</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Potri.001G372300</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AT2G34710.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>−3.29</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.46</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Controls adaxial–abaxial patterning</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>PHB</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ptp.548.1.S1_x_at</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>−3.14</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.37</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>PHB</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PtpAffx.38907.1.S1_at</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Potri.011G098300</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AT2G34710.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>−2.21</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.79</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Controls adaxial–abaxial patterning</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>ANT</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PtpAffx.1799.1.A1_at</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Potri.014G008100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AT4G37750.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>−4.26</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−1.19</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Required for control of cell proliferation</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>ANT</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PtpAffx.211416.1.S1_at</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>−3.23</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.77</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>ANT</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PtpAffx.147010.1.A1_at</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Potri.002G114800</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AT4G37750.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>−1.41</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.80</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Required for control of cell proliferation</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>ANT</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">PtpAffx.34524.3.A1_a_at</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Potri.005G148400</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AT4G37750.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>−4.35</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−2.21</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Required for control of cell proliferation</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s3b5" disp-level="3"><title>Variation under well-watered conditions</title><p>To elucidate constitutive differences in gene expression between the Spanish and Italian genotypes that are present in well-watered conditions, a comparison was also completed for the control data (see <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://treephys.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/treephys/tpw017/-/DC1" ext-link-type="uri">Table S6 available as Supplementary Data at <italic>Tree Physiology</italic> Online</ext-link>). Two hundred and fifty-two up-regulated and 284 down-regulated transcripts were identified in Sp2 compared with Ita (Figure <xref rid="TPW017F6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>c). The AgriGO analysis showed enriched GO terms differentially expressed between Sp2 and Ita in well-watered conditions, and these were generally related to secondary metabolism. Also up-regulated in the Spanish genotype were <italic>ERD1</italic> (<italic>EARLY RESPONSE TO DEHYDRATION 1</italic>) and <italic>RD21</italic> (<italic>RESPONSIVE TO DEHYDRATION 21</italic>).</p></sec><sec id="s3b6" disp-level="3"><title>Real-time qPCR</title><p>Microarray results were validated by real-time qPCR on four candidate genes selected after microarray analysis. Gene expression was quantified for additional genotypes that were not included in the microarray experiment: Fr1 from France and NL from the Netherlands (see <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://treephys.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/treephys/tpw017/-/DC1" ext-link-type="uri">Figure S3 available as Supplementary Data at <italic>Tree Physiology</italic> Online</ext-link>). Real-time qPCR values were expressed in response to drought for each genotype. <italic>SPEECHLESS</italic> expression ratios were lower in response to drought in both Ita and Sp2, although this response was greater in Ita (<italic>F</italic><sub>3,32</sub> = 9.311, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.001, see <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://treephys.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/treephys/tpw017/-/DC1" ext-link-type="uri">Figure S3 available as Supplementary Data at <italic>Tree Physiology</italic> Online</ext-link>). The expression ratios of <italic>ERECTA</italic> were reduced in response to drought with no significant difference between genotypes (<italic>F</italic><sub>3,32</sub> = 0.845, <italic>P</italic> = 0.48, see <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://treephys.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/treephys/tpw017/-/DC1" ext-link-type="uri">Figure S3 available as Supplementary Data at <italic>Tree Physiology</italic> Online</ext-link>).</p></sec></sec></sec><sec id="s4" disp-level="1"><title>Discussion</title><p>Our analysis has revealed significant natural variation between populations of black poplar originating from contrasting climatic conditions within Europe. By combining a common garden approach with manipulative experiments and genome-wide gene expression, this study provides considerable insight into the intraspecific variation in drought tolerance for this important keystone riparian tree species. We have identified transcriptome and trait differences that suggest important adaptive mechanisms that exist within the species.</p><p>From results at a single site in northern Europe under well-watered conditions, leaf, cell and stem size traits differed among genotypes of <italic>P. nigra</italic> (Figure <xref rid="TPW017F1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>), we hypothesize that Spanish and southern French genotypes have smaller leaves as an adaptation to drought developed in their native environment. Similar observations have been drawn for two other genotypes of <italic>P. nigra</italic> from contrasting northern and southern (water limited) environments in Italy (<xref rid="TPW017C58" ref-type="bibr">Regier et al. 2009</xref>, <xref rid="TPW017C16" ref-type="bibr">Cocozza et al. 2010</xref>).</p><p>For the population of <italic>P. nigra</italic>, genotypic variation was clear in Δ<sup>13</sup>C and varied with site of origin (Figure <xref rid="TPW017F1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). Wood Δ<sup>13</sup>C was lower in populations from the north and east of Europe, such as The Netherlands, Germany and northern Italy, and this indicates higher WUE. However, these trees were collected from wet environments in Europe, comparable to the conditions in the common garden, suggesting that they are particularly well adapted to the Belgian climate. On the other hand, and perhaps counter-intuitively, Spanish and southern French populations had the highest Δ<sup>13</sup>C, suggesting a lower WUE and poor control of water loss without a reduction in photosynthesis or lowered photosynthetic rates but with unchanged <italic>g</italic><sub>s</sub>. In contrast to Δ<sup>13</sup>C, no significant differences were observed between populations in SI (a measure of stomatal patterning), although there was a trend of increased stomatal numbers in northern and eastern genotypes. Given the potential for stomatal patterning and related genes to affect <italic>g</italic><sub>s</sub> and thus WUE (<xref rid="TPW017C82" ref-type="bibr">Woodward et al. 2002</xref>, <xref rid="TPW017C46" ref-type="bibr">Masle et al. 2005</xref>, <xref rid="TPW017C60" ref-type="bibr">Roussel et al. 2009</xref>), this lack of significance was surprising. Any adaptation to water deficit by the small-leaf morphotypes, characteristic of Spanish trees, is likely, however, to involve additional physiological pathways that are distinct from those controlling stomatal development. It is also possible that stomatal patterning is phenotypically plastic, with differential stomatal patterning occurring in leaves in response to water deficit, and our data for gene expression from the drought experiment would support this contention.</p><p>Contrasting genotypes were identified from the moderate drought experiment on genotypes from four locations (Figure <xref rid="TPW017F3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>a), with different adaptive mechanisms apparent for response to drought stress. The ‘north eastern’ genotype is characteristic of the northern Italian and Netherlands genotypes, originating from areas of high precipitation, where tree productivity and leaf area development are generally high but where height growth and new leaf formation decreased dramatically following the onset of drought. In contrast, a ‘southern’ genotype, from a region of low precipitation, is characterized by the Spanish and southerly French populations. Slow-growing with small leaves, these genotypes responded to drought with rapid stomatal closure, with the maintenance of leaf expansion (for Sp2) and formation (at least in the extreme example of Sp2), but with some leaf loss. Rapid stomatal closure only 5 days after drought in French and Spanish genotypes supports the idea that variation in stomatal behaviour can exist within species, as was shown by <xref rid="TPW017C66" ref-type="bibr">Sparks and Black (1999)</xref> in four populations of <italic>P. trichocarpa</italic> originating from contrasting environments.</p><p>Stomatal closure is a biological process to avoid water loss in the event of drought stress but can have other physiological consequences as it can inhibit photosynthesis (<xref rid="TPW017C19" ref-type="bibr">Cornic 2000</xref>). There is a trend in our results, which indicates that Sp2 closed stomata more in response to drought when compared with Ita (5DAD and 15DAD) and this correlated with reduced Δ<sup>13</sup>C under drought, suggesting an increase in WUE in droughted conditions. In a study of δ<sup>13</sup>C in beech planted in different sites throughout Europe, the highest values (thus the lowest values of Δ<sup>13</sup>C) were observed in the most southern location in France (<xref rid="TPW017C38" ref-type="bibr">Keitel et al. 2006</xref>). <xref rid="TPW017C48" ref-type="bibr">Monclus et al. (2005)</xref> studied different genotypes of <italic>Populus</italic> (tolerant and non-tolerant to drought) and showed that the drought-tolerant trees tended to decrease in Δ<sup>13</sup>C, but the inverse was observed for the non-tolerant genotypes.</p><p>Genotypes from Spain and Italy were selected for gene expression analyses because their sites of origin differed markedly in rainfall but not temperature, and thus likely represented contrasting strategies for response to soil water deficits. Given the controlled application of water deficit, with controlled constant temperature in this experiment, it was surprising to see that gene expression changes differed so markedly between the two genotypes, with more than eight times the number of differentially expressed genes observed in the Ita compared with the Sp2 genotype. It is remarkable that only 901 transcripts were commonly expressed in response to drought for both genotypes, considering &gt;8000 changes in gene expression were observed in total. This result strongly suggests that the Spanish and Italian genotypes are differentially adapted to drought stress and that this involves considerable plasticity in gene expression—manifested in contrasting phenotypic acclimation to the imposed stress. This result is similar to that from Mediterranean species, which has suggested that phenotypic plasticity is lower in plants from low resource environments as part of a conservative resource-use strategy (<xref rid="TPW017C75" ref-type="bibr">Valladares et al. 2000</xref>). These contrasting patterns of gene expression in <italic>P. nigra</italic>, and their associated phenotypes, provide important clues to aid our understanding of adaptation. This will help to ensure the availability of a resilient gene pool as drought stress increases across Europe, which is a valuable resource for future management and conservation of black poplar.</p><p>A larger number of GO groups related to ‘response to stimulus’ were significantly enriched in Ita compared with in Sp2, suggesting a highly water stress-responsive gene expression pattern in the Ita trees (Figure <xref rid="TPW017F9" ref-type="fig">9</xref>). Similar conclusions were drawn for salt-stressed (<xref rid="TPW017C79" ref-type="bibr">Walia et al. 2005</xref>, <xref rid="TPW017C80" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>) and drought-stressed (<xref rid="TPW017C20" ref-type="bibr">Degenkolbe et al. 2009</xref>) rice genotypes. When comparing two genotypes of potatoes, <xref rid="TPW017C61" ref-type="bibr">Schafleitner et al. (2007)</xref> observed only 186 up-regulated and 77 down-regulated genes in common, while 1713 genes were expressed in total in response to drought.
</p><fig id="TPW017F9" position="float"><?disp-level 2?><label>Figure 9.</label><caption><p>Summary of the response to drought in two genotypes of <italic>P. nigra</italic>.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="image" xlink:href="tpw01709.jpg"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/d4bd/4969554/51c450c6a557/tpw01709.jpg?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?><?image-server-status LOAD_COMPLETED?><?original-height 3795?><?original-width 2978?><?scaled-height 948?><?scaled-width 744?></graphic><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" content-type="thumb" xlink:href="tpw01709.gif"><?cloudpmc-path blobs/d4bd/4969554/7d62913dba98/tpw01709.gif?><?cloudpmc-bucket cdn?></graphic></alternatives></fig><p>There are two important phenotypic traits that underpin drought tolerance and appear to be key to understanding genomic plasticity and adaptation in these contrasting genotypes of black poplar. These traits are linked to leaf development and stomatal patterning and contribute to drought tolerance. Leaf size determines leaf and canopy transpiration (<xref rid="TPW017C54" ref-type="bibr">Radin et al. 1994</xref>, <xref rid="TPW017C39" ref-type="bibr">Levi et al. 2009</xref>, <xref rid="TPW017C5" ref-type="bibr">Ashraf 2010</xref>) and is also tightly related to yield, an important trait linked to fitness (<xref rid="TPW017C55" ref-type="bibr">Rae et al. 2004</xref>, <xref rid="TPW017C48" ref-type="bibr">Monclus et al. 2005</xref>). Leaf production and leaf loss represent important adaptive mechanisms enabling long-lived trees to moderate the amount of transpiring leaf surface area. Furthermore, stomatal aperture and stomatal number both contribute to the control of transpiration, leaf-level WUE and drought tolerance (<xref rid="TPW017C52" ref-type="bibr">Nilson and Assmann 2007</xref>). While both genotypes showed reduced leaf expansion in response to drought, for the Ita genotype, this reduction was dramatic (&lt;50%), while for Sp2, it was moderate (&lt;20%). Changes in gene expression concur with these different developmental responses to drought. Down-regulation of genes involved in balance between shoot apical meristem activity and the initiation, and development of leaf primordia such as <italic>ANT</italic>, <italic>PHB</italic>, <italic>AS1</italic>, <italic>AS2</italic> and <italic>CLV1</italic> concur with these developmental responses to drought in the Italian genotype, while only <italic>AS1</italic> and <italic>AS2</italic> were down-regulated in Sp2 (Table <xref rid="TPW017TB3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). Together with the drastic down-regulation of processes related to growth, development and cell division revealed by PAGE analysis, these results suggest that cell proliferation, leaf expansion and leaf size would be reduced for the Ita genotype in response to drought, while the Sp2 genotype would be less affected. Ita expression is thus more concentrated in reacting to stress rather than maintaining leaf development (Figure <xref rid="TPW017F9" ref-type="fig">9</xref>), and this is supported by a drastic down-regulation of processes linked to cell division revealed by GO analysis.</p><p>Similarly, striking differences in genes controlling stomatal initiation and number were observed in response to drought for Spanish and Italian genotypes. Stomata regulate CO<sub>2</sub> and water-vapour exchange between leaves and the atmosphere (<xref rid="TPW017C43" ref-type="bibr">MacAlister et al. 2007</xref>) and prevent water loss through partial stomatal closure. Although the genetic control of stomatal initiation and patterning is now well documented (<xref rid="TPW017C7" ref-type="bibr">Barton 2007</xref>, <xref rid="TPW017C29" ref-type="bibr">Gray 2007</xref>, <xref rid="TPW017C12" ref-type="bibr">Casson and Hetherington 2010</xref>, <xref rid="TPW017C71" ref-type="bibr">Torii 2015</xref>), less is known about how the environment interacts with the control of stomatal patterning, although genes regulating the development of stomata have also been discovered in response to light (<xref rid="TPW017C13" ref-type="bibr">Casson et al. 2009</xref>), CO<sub>2</sub> (<xref rid="TPW017C30" ref-type="bibr">Gray et al. 2000</xref>, <xref rid="TPW017C34" ref-type="bibr">Hu et al. 2010</xref>) and drought (<xref rid="TPW017C46" ref-type="bibr">Masle et al. 2005</xref>). Unfortunately stomatal patterning was not measured here, but our ongoing research suggests that patterning differs depending on genotype (H. Smith, unpublished data).</p><p>Several stomatal patterning genes that negatively regulate stomatal number were down-regulated in response to drought for the Italian genotype including <italic>TMM</italic> (<italic>TOO MANY MOUTHS</italic>), <italic>ERECTA</italic> and <italic>ERL1</italic> (<italic>ERECTA-LIKE 1</italic>, Figure <xref rid="TPW017F8" ref-type="fig">8</xref>). In particular, there is strong evidence that increased transcript abundance in <italic>ERECTA</italic> is linked to declining stomatal numbers, and that <italic>ERECTA</italic> acts to regulate the initial decision of cells to enter the stomatal developmental pathway (<xref rid="TPW017C63" ref-type="bibr">Shpak et al. 2007</xref>). Two positive regulators of stomatal development were also down-regulated—<italic>SPEECHLESS</italic> and <italic>MUTE</italic>. Overall, the down-regulation of <italic>ERECTA</italic>, <italic>ERL1</italic> and <italic>TMM</italic> in the Italian genotype suggests that the formation of stomata was stimulated in response to drought. Few changes in gene expression for genes that regulate stomatal numbers were apparent for the Spanish ecotype; only the <italic>ERECTA</italic> gene showed any response to drought, and this could still be significant. The stomatal patterning phenotype remains to be tested in these <italic>P. nigra</italic> trees.</p><p>Although our prediction is for increased stomatal numbers in response to drought for Ita, this has not yet been tested but is the subject of future research alongside RNA-Seq analysis of guard cell and epidermal gene expression. The stimulation of stomatal initiation in response to drought is somewhat counter-intuitive, and recent reports for <italic>P. balsamifera</italic> showed reduced stomatal numbers following drought treatment (<xref rid="TPW017C32" ref-type="bibr">Hamanishi et al. 2012</xref>). These authors also assessed expression of several stomatal patterning genes and differences between two commercial genotypes were apparent, although they were often inconsistent across several sampling times. Nevertheless, they reinforce the concept that the regulation of stomatal numbers varies intraspecifically and may be an important control point to elucidate differences in adaptation to drought in the genus <italic>Populus</italic> (<xref rid="TPW017C60" ref-type="bibr">Roussel et al. 2009</xref>).</p><p>In summary, we have identified significant differences in response to drought for black poplar genotypes collected from dry and wet environments across Europe. ‘Southern’ Spanish trees are well adapted to slow growth in droughted conditions, producing small leaves and partially closed stomata, with a higher intrinsic WUE, while Italian and ‘north eastern’ trees demonstrate a dramatic response to drought with reduced growth and increased stomatal formation. We hypothesize, therefore, that each of these strategies may be of value, depending on the likely frequency and duration of drought in a particular environment. Importantly here, we have identified a suite of genes that will be the focus of our future research using reverse genetic approaches and testing material in the field in contrasting drought environments. Thus, screening for functional genomic and genetic variation in genotypes from diverse geographic locations under drought stress is a powerful strategy to inform the conservation and management of germplasm resources in a future, changing climate and should be exploited more widely in these difficult-to-study, long-lived but critical plants that contribute to timber, fuel, fibre and ecosystem service provision on a global scale.</p></sec><sec id="s5" disp-level="1"><title>Supplementary data</title><p><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://treephys.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/treephys/tpw017/-/DC1" ext-link-type="uri">Supplementary data for this article are available at <italic>Tree Physiology</italic> Online</ext-link>.</p></sec><sec id="s6" disp-level="1"><title>Conflict of interest</title><p>None declared.</p></sec><sec id="s7" disp-level="1"><title>Funding</title><p>This research was supported by the European Commission through the Directorate General Research within the Fifth Framework for Research – Quality of Life and Management of the Living Resources Programme, contact No. QLK5-CT-2002-00953 (POPYOMICs), within the Sixth Framework for Research as part of the Network of Excellence EVOLTREE, contract No. 016322 – Sustainable development, Global Change and Ecosystems Programme and through the Seventh Framework for Research, Food Agriculture and Fisheries, Biotechnology, within the project ENERGYPOPLAR, contract No. FP7-211917 and WATBIO, contract No. FP7-311929. H.T. was supported by a PhD studentship from NERC. Funding to pay the Open Access publication charges for this article was provided by RCUK.</p></sec><sec id="sec24" disp-level="1"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material id="PMC_1" position="float"><?disp-level 2?><caption><title>Supplementary Data</title></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="supp_36_7_909__index.html" mimetype="text" mime-subtype="html"><?cloudpmc-path d4bd/4969554/81941f79c840/supp_36_7_909__index.html?><?cloudpmc-bucket app?><?size 1713?></media></supplementary-material></sec><sec id="ack1" sec-type="ack" disp-level="1"><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>The authors thank P.J. Tricker, N.R. Street, A.M. Rae, C. Dixon, S. Milner and B. Street for field and laboratory assistance, K. Schamp for field assistance, M.J. Tallis for preliminary data analysis and Forest Research for grinding the wood samples.</p></sec><sec id="ref-list1" sec-type="ref-list" disp-level="1"><title>References</title><sec id="ref-list1_sec2" disp-level="2"><ref-list><ref id="TPW017C1"><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Abràmoff MD, Magelhães PJ, Ram SJ (2004) Image processing with ImageJ. Biophotonics Int
11:36–42.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Biophotonics Int&amp;title=Image processing with ImageJ&amp;author=MD Abràmoff&amp;author=PJ Magelhães&amp;author=SJ Ram&amp;volume=11&amp;publication_year=2004&amp;pages=36-42&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="TPW017C3"><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Alberto FJ, Aitkin AN, Alia R et al.  (2013) Potential for evolutionary responses to climate change—evidence from tree populations. Glob Change Biol
19:1645–1661. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/gcb.12181" ext-link-type="uri">doi:10.1111/gcb.12181</ext-link></named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1111/gcb.12181"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC3664019"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="23505261"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Glob Change Biol&amp;title=Potential for evolutionary responses to climate change—evidence from tree populations&amp;author=FJ Alberto&amp;author=AN Aitkin&amp;author=R Alia&amp;volume=19&amp;publication_year=2013&amp;pages=1645-1661&amp;pmid=23505261&amp;doi=10.1111/gcb.12181&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="TPW017C4"><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Allen CD, Macalady AK, Chencouni H et al.  (2010) A global overview of drought and heat-induced tree mortality reveals emerging climate change risks for forests. For Ecol Manag
259:660–684. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.foreco.2009.09.001" ext-link-type="uri">doi:10.1016/j.foreco.2009.09.001</ext-link></named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=For Ecol Manag&amp;title=A global overview of drought and heat-induced tree mortality reveals emerging climate change risks for forests&amp;author=CD Allen&amp;author=AK Macalady&amp;author=H Chencouni&amp;volume=259&amp;publication_year=2010&amp;pages=660-684&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="TPW017C5"><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Ashraf M. (2010) Introducing drought tolerance in plants: recent advances. Biotechnol Adv
28:169–183. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.biotechadv.2009.11.005" ext-link-type="uri">doi:10.1016/j.biotechadv.2009.11.005</ext-link></named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/j.biotechadv.2009.11.005"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="19914371"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Biotechnol Adv&amp;title=Introducing drought tolerance in plants: recent advances&amp;author=M Ashraf&amp;volume=28&amp;publication_year=2010&amp;pages=169-183&amp;pmid=19914371&amp;doi=10.1016/j.biotechadv.2009.11.005&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="TPW017C6"><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Atwell S, Huang YS, Vilhjálmsson BJ et al.  (2010) Genome-wide association study of 107 phenotypes in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> inbred lines. Nature
465:627–631. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/nature08800" ext-link-type="uri">doi:10.1038/nature08800</ext-link></named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1038/nature08800"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC3023908"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="20336072"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Nature&amp;title=Genome-wide association study of 107 phenotypes in Arabidopsis thaliana inbred lines&amp;author=S Atwell&amp;author=YS Huang&amp;author=BJ Vilhjálmsson&amp;volume=465&amp;publication_year=2010&amp;pages=627-631&amp;pmid=20336072&amp;doi=10.1038/nature08800&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="TPW017C7"><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Barton MK. (2007) Making holes in leaves: promoting cell state transitions in stomatal development. Plant Cell
19:1140–1143. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1105/tpc.107.051177" ext-link-type="uri">doi:10.1105/tpc.107.051177</ext-link></named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1105/tpc.107.051177"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC1913752"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="17468260"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Plant Cell&amp;title=Making holes in leaves: promoting cell state transitions in stomatal development&amp;author=MK Barton&amp;volume=19&amp;publication_year=2007&amp;pages=1140-1143&amp;pmid=17468260&amp;doi=10.1105/tpc.107.051177&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="TPW017C8"><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Benito Garzón M, Alía R, Robson M, Zavala MA (2011) Intra-specific variability and plasticity influence potential tree species distributions under climate change. Glob Ecol Biogeogr
20:766–778. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1466-8238.2010.00646.x" ext-link-type="uri">doi:10.1111/j.1466-8238.2010.00646.x</ext-link></named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Glob Ecol Biogeogr&amp;title=Intra-specific variability and plasticity influence potential tree species distributions under climate change&amp;author=M Benito Garzón&amp;author=R Alía&amp;author=M Robson&amp;author=MA Zavala&amp;volume=20&amp;publication_year=2011&amp;pages=766-778&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="TPW017C9"><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Bogeat-Triboulot M-B, Brosché M, Renaut J et al.  (2007) Gradual soil water depletion results in reversible changes of gene expression, protein profiles, ecophysiology, and growth performance in <italic>Populus euphratica</italic>, a poplar growing in arid regions. Plant Physiol
143:876–892. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1104/pp.106.088708" ext-link-type="uri">doi:10.1104/pp.106.088708</ext-link></named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1104/pp.106.088708"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC1803728"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="17158588"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Plant Physiol&amp;title=Gradual soil water depletion results in reversible changes of gene expression, protein profiles, ecophysiology, and growth performance in Populus euphratica, a poplar growing in arid regions&amp;author=M-B Bogeat-Triboulot&amp;author=M Brosché&amp;author=J Renaut&amp;volume=143&amp;publication_year=2007&amp;pages=876-892&amp;pmid=17158588&amp;doi=10.1104/pp.106.088708&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="TPW017C10"><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Bréda N, Badeau V (2008) Forest tree responses to extreme drought and some biotic events: towards a selection according to hazard tolerance. C R Geosci
340:651–662. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.crte.2008.08.003" ext-link-type="uri">doi:10.1016/j.crte.2008.08.003</ext-link></named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=C R Geosci&amp;title=Forest tree responses to extreme drought and some biotic events: towards a selection according to hazard tolerance&amp;author=N Bréda&amp;author=V Badeau&amp;volume=340&amp;publication_year=2008&amp;pages=651-662&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="TPW017C11"><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Bussotti F, Pollastrini M, Holland V, Brüggemann W (2015) Functional traits and adaptive capacity of European forests to climate change. Environ Exp Bot
111:91–113. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.envexpbot.2014.11.006" ext-link-type="uri">doi:10.1016/j.envexpbot.2014.11.006</ext-link></named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Environ Exp Bot&amp;title=Functional traits and adaptive capacity of European forests to climate change&amp;author=F Bussotti&amp;author=M Pollastrini&amp;author=V Holland&amp;author=W Brüggemann&amp;volume=111&amp;publication_year=2015&amp;pages=91-113&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="TPW017C12"><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Casson SA, Hetherington AM (2010) Environmental regulation of stomatal development. Curr Opin Plant Biol
13:90–95. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.pbi.2009.08.005" ext-link-type="uri">doi:10.1016/j.pbi.2009.08.005</ext-link></named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/j.pbi.2009.08.005"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="19781980"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Curr Opin Plant Biol&amp;title=Environmental regulation of stomatal development&amp;author=SA Casson&amp;author=AM Hetherington&amp;volume=13&amp;publication_year=2010&amp;pages=90-95&amp;pmid=19781980&amp;doi=10.1016/j.pbi.2009.08.005&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="TPW017C13"><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Casson SA, Franklin KA, Gray JE, Grierson CS, Whitelam GC, Hetherington AM (2009) Phytochrome B and <italic>PIF4</italic> regulate stomatal development in response to light quantity. Curr Biol
19:229–234. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.cub.2008.12.046" ext-link-type="uri">doi:10.1016/j.cub.2008.12.046</ext-link></named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/j.cub.2008.12.046"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="19185498"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Curr Biol&amp;title=Phytochrome B and PIF4 regulate stomatal development in response to light quantity&amp;author=SA Casson&amp;author=KA Franklin&amp;author=JE Gray&amp;author=CS Grierson&amp;author=GC Whitelam&amp;volume=19&amp;publication_year=2009&amp;pages=229-234&amp;pmid=19185498&amp;doi=10.1016/j.cub.2008.12.046&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="TPW017C14"><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Chang S, Puryear J, Cairney J (1993) A simple and efficient method for isolating RNA from pine trees. Plant Mol Biol Rep
11:113–116. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/BF02670468" ext-link-type="uri">doi:10.1007/BF02670468</ext-link></named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Plant Mol Biol Rep&amp;title=A simple and efficient method for isolating RNA from pine trees&amp;author=S Chang&amp;author=J Puryear&amp;author=J Cairney&amp;volume=11&amp;publication_year=1993&amp;pages=113-116&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="TPW017C16"><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Cocozza C, Cherubini P, Regier N, Saurer M, Frey B, Tognetti R (2010) Early effects of water deficit on two parental clones of <italic>Populus nigra</italic> grown under different environmental conditions. Funct Plant Biol
37:244–254. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1071/FP09156" ext-link-type="uri">doi:10.1071/FP09156</ext-link></named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Funct Plant Biol&amp;title=Early effects of water deficit on two parental clones of Populus nigra grown under different environmental conditions&amp;author=C Cocozza&amp;author=P Cherubini&amp;author=N Regier&amp;author=M Saurer&amp;author=B Frey&amp;volume=37&amp;publication_year=2010&amp;pages=244-254&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="TPW017C17"><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Cohen D, Bogeat-Triboulot M-B, Tisserant E et al.  (2010) Comparative transcriptomics of drought responses in <italic>Populus</italic>: a meta-analysis of genome-wide expression profiling in mature leaves and root apices across two genotypes. BMC Genom
11:630
<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1186/1471-2164-11-630" ext-link-type="uri">doi:10.1186/1471-2164-11-630</ext-link></named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1186/1471-2164-11-630"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC3091765"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="21073700"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=BMC Genom&amp;title=Comparative transcriptomics of drought responses in Populus: a meta-analysis of genome-wide expression profiling in mature leaves and root apices across two genotypes&amp;author=D Cohen&amp;author=M-B Bogeat-Triboulot&amp;author=E Tisserant&amp;volume=11&amp;publication_year=2010&amp;pages=630&amp;pmid=21073700&amp;doi=10.1186/1471-2164-11-630&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="TPW017C18"><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Condon AG, Richards RA, Rebetzke GJ, Farquhar GD (2002) Improving intrinsic water-use efficiency and crop yield. Crop Sci
42:122–131. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.2135/cropsci2002.0122" ext-link-type="uri">doi:10.2135/cropsci2002.0122</ext-link></named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.2135/cropsci2002.1220"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="11756262"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Crop Sci&amp;title=Improving intrinsic water-use efficiency and crop yield&amp;author=AG Condon&amp;author=RA Richards&amp;author=GJ Rebetzke&amp;author=GD Farquhar&amp;volume=42&amp;publication_year=2002&amp;pages=122-131&amp;pmid=11756262&amp;doi=10.2135/cropsci2002.1220&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="TPW017C19"><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Cornic G. (2000) Drought stress inhibits photosynthesis by decreasing stomatal aperture—not by affecting ATP synthesis. Trends Plant Sci
5:187–188. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/S1360-1385(00)01625-3" ext-link-type="uri">doi:10.1016/S1360-1385(00)01625-3</ext-link></named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Trends Plant Sci&amp;title=Drought stress inhibits photosynthesis by decreasing stomatal aperture—not by affecting ATP synthesis&amp;author=G Cornic&amp;volume=5&amp;publication_year=2000&amp;pages=187-188&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="TPW017C20"><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Degenkolbe T, Thi Do P, Zuther E, Repsilber D, Walther D, Hincha DK, Köhl KI (2009) Expression profiling of rice cultivars differing in their tolerance to long-term drought stress. Plant Mol Biol
69:133–153. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s11103-008-9412-7" ext-link-type="uri">doi:10.1007/s11103-008-9412-7</ext-link></named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1007/s11103-008-9412-7"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC2709230"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="18931976"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Plant Mol Biol&amp;title=Expression profiling of rice cultivars differing in their tolerance to long-term drought stress&amp;author=T Degenkolbe&amp;author=P Thi Do&amp;author=E Zuther&amp;author=D Repsilber&amp;author=D Walther&amp;volume=69&amp;publication_year=2009&amp;pages=133-153&amp;pmid=18931976&amp;doi=10.1007/s11103-008-9412-7&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="TPW017C21"><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Dillen SY, Marron N, Koch B, Ceulemans R (2008) Genetic variation of stomatal traits and carbon isotope discrimination in two hybrid Poplar families (<italic>Populus deltoides</italic> ‘S9-2’ × <italic>P. nigra</italic> ‘Ghoy’ and <italic>P. deltoides</italic> ‘S9-2’ × <italic>P. trichocarpa</italic> ‘V24’). Ann Bot
102:399–407. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/aob/mcn107" ext-link-type="uri">doi:10.1093/aob/mcn107</ext-link></named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1093/aob/mcn107"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC2701808"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="18587131"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Ann Bot&amp;title=Genetic variation of stomatal traits and carbon isotope discrimination in two hybrid Poplar families (Populus deltoides ‘S9-2’ × P. nigra ‘Ghoy’ and P. deltoides ‘S9-2’ × P. trichocarpa ‘V24’)&amp;author=SY Dillen&amp;author=N Marron&amp;author=B Koch&amp;author=R Ceulemans&amp;volume=102&amp;publication_year=2008&amp;pages=399-407&amp;pmid=18587131&amp;doi=10.1093/aob/mcn107&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="TPW017C22"><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Dreyer E, Bogeat-Triboulot M-B, Le Thiec D, Guehl J-M, Brignolas F, Villar M, Bastien C, Martin F, Kohler A (2004) Tolérance des peupliers à la sécheresse: peut-on espérer l’améliorer. Biofutur
247:54–58.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Biofutur&amp;title=Tolérance des peupliers à la sécheresse: peut-on espérer l’améliorer&amp;author=E Dreyer&amp;author=M-B Bogeat-Triboulot&amp;author=D Le Thiec&amp;author=J-M Guehl&amp;author=F Brignolas&amp;volume=247&amp;publication_year=2004&amp;pages=54-58&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="TPW017C23"><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Du Z, Zhou K, Ling Y, Zhang Z, Su Z (2010) agriGO: a GO analysis toolkit for the agricultural community. Nucleic Acids Res
38:W64–W70. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/nar/gkq310" ext-link-type="uri">doi:10.1093/nar/gkq310</ext-link></named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1093/nar/gkq310"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC2896167"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="20435677"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Nucleic Acids Res&amp;title=agriGO: a GO analysis toolkit for the agricultural community&amp;author=Z Du&amp;author=K Zhou&amp;author=Y Ling&amp;author=Z Zhang&amp;author=Z Su&amp;volume=38&amp;publication_year=2010&amp;pages=W64-W70&amp;pmid=20435677&amp;doi=10.1093/nar/gkq310&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="TPW017C24"><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Farquhar GD, Richard RA (1984) Isotopic composition of plant carbon correlates with water-use efficiency of wheat genotypes. Aust J Plant Physiol
11:539–552. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1071/PP9840539" ext-link-type="uri">doi:10.1071/PP9840539</ext-link></named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Aust J Plant Physiol&amp;title=Isotopic composition of plant carbon correlates with water-use efficiency of wheat genotypes&amp;author=GD Farquhar&amp;author=RA Richard&amp;volume=11&amp;publication_year=1984&amp;pages=539-552&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="TPW017C25"><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Farquhar GD, Ehleringer JR, Hubick KT (1989) Carbon isotope discrimination and photosynthesis. Annu Rev Plant Physiol Plant Mol Biol
40:503–537. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1146/annurev.pp.40.060189.002443" ext-link-type="uri">doi:10.1146/annurev.pp.40.060189.002443</ext-link></named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Annu Rev Plant Physiol Plant Mol Biol&amp;title=Carbon isotope discrimination and photosynthesis&amp;author=GD Farquhar&amp;author=JR Ehleringer&amp;author=KT Hubick&amp;volume=40&amp;publication_year=1989&amp;pages=503-537&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="TPW017C27"><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Gardner SDL, Taylor G, Bosac C (1995) Leaf growth of hybrid poplar following exposure to elevated CO<sub>2</sub>
. New Phytol
131:81–90. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1469-8137.1995.tb03057.x" ext-link-type="uri">doi:10.1111/j.1469-8137.1995.tb03057.x</ext-link></named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1111/j.1469-8137.1995.tb03057.x"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="33863167"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=New Phytol&amp;title=Leaf growth of hybrid poplar following exposure to elevated CO2&amp;author=SDL Gardner&amp;author=G Taylor&amp;author=C Bosac&amp;volume=131&amp;publication_year=1995&amp;pages=81-90&amp;pmid=33863167&amp;doi=10.1111/j.1469-8137.1995.tb03057.x&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="TPW017C28"><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Gaudet M, Jorge V, Paolucci I, Beritognolo I, Scarascia Mugnozza G, Sabatti M (2008) Genetic linkage maps of <italic>Populus nigra</italic> L. including AFLPs, SSRs, SNPs, and sex trait. Tree Genet Genomes
4:25–36. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s11295-007-0085-1" ext-link-type="uri">doi:10.1007/s11295-007-0085-1</ext-link></named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Tree Genet Genomes&amp;title=Genetic linkage maps of Populus nigra L. including AFLPs, SSRs, SNPs, and sex trait&amp;author=M Gaudet&amp;author=V Jorge&amp;author=I Paolucci&amp;author=I Beritognolo&amp;author=G Scarascia Mugnozza&amp;volume=4&amp;publication_year=2008&amp;pages=25-36&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="TPW017C29"><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Gray JE. (2007) Plant development: three steps for stomata. Curr Biol
17:R213–R215. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.cub.2007.01.032" ext-link-type="uri">doi:10.1016/j.cub.2007.01.032</ext-link></named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/j.cub.2007.01.032"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="17371761"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Curr Biol&amp;title=Plant development: three steps for stomata&amp;author=JE Gray&amp;volume=17&amp;publication_year=2007&amp;pages=R213-R215&amp;pmid=17371761&amp;doi=10.1016/j.cub.2007.01.032&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="TPW017C30"><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Gray JE, Holroyd GH, van der Lee FM, Bahrami AR, Sijmons PC, Woodward FI, Schuch W, Hetherington AM (2000) The <italic>HIC</italic> signalling pathway links CO<sub>2</sub> perception to stomatal development. Nature
408:713–716. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/35047071" ext-link-type="uri">doi:10.1038/35047071</ext-link></named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1038/35047071"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="11130071"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Nature&amp;title=The HIC signalling pathway links CO2 perception to stomatal development&amp;author=JE Gray&amp;author=GH Holroyd&amp;author=FM van der Lee&amp;author=AR Bahrami&amp;author=PC Sijmons&amp;volume=408&amp;publication_year=2000&amp;pages=713-716&amp;pmid=11130071&amp;doi=10.1038/35047071&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="TPW017C31"><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Hamanishi E, Raj S, Wilkins O, Thomas BR, Mansfield SD, Plant AL, Campbell MM (2010) Intraspecific variation in the <italic>Populus balsamifera</italic> drought transcriptome. Plant Cell Environ
33:1742–1755. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1365-3040.2010.02179.x" ext-link-type="uri">doi:10.1111/j.1365-3040.2010.02179.x</ext-link></named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1111/j.1365-3040.2010.02179.x"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="20525001"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Plant Cell Environ&amp;title=Intraspecific variation in the Populus balsamifera drought transcriptome&amp;author=E Hamanishi&amp;author=S Raj&amp;author=O Wilkins&amp;author=BR Thomas&amp;author=SD Mansfield&amp;volume=33&amp;publication_year=2010&amp;pages=1742-1755&amp;pmid=20525001&amp;doi=10.1111/j.1365-3040.2010.02179.x&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="TPW017C32"><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Hamanishi E, Thomas BR, Campbell MM (2012) Drought induces alterations in the stomatal development program in <italic>Populus</italic>. J Exp Bot
63:4959–4971. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/jxb/ers177" ext-link-type="uri">doi:10.1093/jxb/ers177</ext-link></named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1093/jxb/ers177"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC3427991"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="22760471"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=J Exp Bot&amp;title=Drought induces alterations in the stomatal development program in Populus&amp;author=E Hamanishi&amp;author=BR Thomas&amp;author=MM Campbell&amp;volume=63&amp;publication_year=2012&amp;pages=4959-4971&amp;pmid=22760471&amp;doi=10.1093/jxb/ers177&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="TPW017C33"><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Hamanishi ET, Barchet GLH, Dauwe R, Mansfield SD, Campbell MM (2015) Poplar trees reconfigure the transcriptome and metabolome in response to drought in a genotype- and time-of-day-dependent manner. BMC Genom
16:329
<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1186/s12864-015-1535-z" ext-link-type="uri">doi:10.1186/s12864-015-1535-z</ext-link></named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1186/s12864-015-1535-z"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC4437445"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="25895923"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=BMC Genom&amp;title=Poplar trees reconfigure the transcriptome and metabolome in response to drought in a genotype- and time-of-day-dependent manner&amp;author=ET Hamanishi&amp;author=GLH Barchet&amp;author=R Dauwe&amp;author=SD Mansfield&amp;author=MM Campbell&amp;volume=16&amp;publication_year=2015&amp;pages=329&amp;pmid=25895923&amp;doi=10.1186/s12864-015-1535-z&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="TPW017C34"><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Hu H, Boisson-Dernier A, Israelsson-Nordström M, Böhmer M, Xue S, Ries A, Godoski J, Kuhn J, Schroeder JI (2010) Carbonic anhydrases are upstream regulators of CO<sub>2</sub>-controlled stomatal movements in guard cells. Nat Cell Biol
12:87–93. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/ncb2009" ext-link-type="uri">doi:10.1038/ncb2009</ext-link></named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1038/ncb2009"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC2906259"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="20010812"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Nat Cell Biol&amp;title=Carbonic anhydrases are upstream regulators of CO2-controlled stomatal movements in guard cells&amp;author=H Hu&amp;author=A Boisson-Dernier&amp;author=M Israelsson-Nordström&amp;author=M Böhmer&amp;author=S Xue&amp;volume=12&amp;publication_year=2010&amp;pages=87-93&amp;pmid=20010812&amp;doi=10.1038/ncb2009&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="TPW017C35"><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Huang X, Xiao X, Zhang S, Korpelainen H, Li C (2009) Leaf morphological and physiological responses to drought and shade in two <italic>Populus cathayana</italic> populations. Biol Plantarum
53:588–592. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s10535-009-0107-y" ext-link-type="uri">doi:10.1007/s10535-009-0107-y</ext-link></named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Biol Plantarum&amp;title=Leaf morphological and physiological responses to drought and shade in two Populus cathayana populations&amp;author=X Huang&amp;author=X Xiao&amp;author=S Zhang&amp;author=H Korpelainen&amp;author=C Li&amp;volume=53&amp;publication_year=2009&amp;pages=588-592&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="TPW017C36"><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">IPCC (2014) Climate Change 2014: Synthesis Report. Contribution of Working Groups I, II and III to the Fifth Assessment Report of the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change. In: Core Writing Team, Pachauri RK, Meyer LA (eds)
IPCC,
Geneva, Switzerland, 151 p.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="title=Climate Change 2014: Synthesis Report. Contribution of Working Groups I, II and III to the Fifth Assessment Report of the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change&amp;publication_year=2014&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="TPW017C37"><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Jansson S, Douglas CJ (2007) <italic>Populus</italic>: a model system for plant biology. Annu Rev Plant Biol
58:435–458. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1146/annurev.arplant.58.032806.103956" ext-link-type="uri">doi:10.1146/annurev.arplant.58.032806.103956</ext-link></named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1146/annurev.arplant.58.032806.103956"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="17280524"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Annu Rev Plant Biol&amp;title=Populus: a model system for plant biology&amp;author=S Jansson&amp;author=CJ Douglas&amp;volume=58&amp;publication_year=2007&amp;pages=435-458&amp;pmid=17280524&amp;doi=10.1146/annurev.arplant.58.032806.103956&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="TPW017C38"><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Keitel C, Matzarakis A, Rennenberg H, Gessler A (2006) Carbon isotopic composition and oxygen isotopic enrichment in phloem and total leaf organic matter of European beech (<italic>Fagus sylvatica</italic> L.) along a climate gradient. Plant Cell Environ
29:1492–1507. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1365-3040.2006.01520.x" ext-link-type="uri">doi:10.1111/j.1365-3040.2006.01520.x</ext-link></named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1111/j.1365-3040.2006.01520.x"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="16898013"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Plant Cell Environ&amp;title=Carbon isotopic composition and oxygen isotopic enrichment in phloem and total leaf organic matter of European beech (Fagus sylvatica L.) along a climate gradient&amp;author=C Keitel&amp;author=A Matzarakis&amp;author=H Rennenberg&amp;author=A Gessler&amp;volume=29&amp;publication_year=2006&amp;pages=1492-1507&amp;pmid=16898013&amp;doi=10.1111/j.1365-3040.2006.01520.x&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="TPW017C39"><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Levi A, Ovnat L, Paterson AH, Saranga Y (2009) Photosynthesis of cotton near-isogenic lines introgressed with QTLs for productivity and drought related traits. Plant Sci
177:88–96. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.plantsci.2009.04.001" ext-link-type="uri">doi:10.1016/j.plantsci.2009.04.001</ext-link></named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1111/j.1399-3054.2010.01438.x"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="21143238"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Plant Sci&amp;title=Photosynthesis of cotton near-isogenic lines introgressed with QTLs for productivity and drought related traits&amp;author=A Levi&amp;author=L Ovnat&amp;author=AH Paterson&amp;author=Y Saranga&amp;volume=177&amp;publication_year=2009&amp;pages=88-96&amp;pmid=21143238&amp;doi=10.1111/j.1399-3054.2010.01438.x&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="TPW017C41"><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Lindner M, Maraschek M, Netherer S et al.  (2010) Climate change impacts, adaptive capacity, and vulnerability of European forest ecosystems. For Ecol Manag
259:698–709. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.foreco.2009.09.023" ext-link-type="uri">doi:10.1016/j.foreco.2009.09.023</ext-link></named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=For Ecol Manag&amp;title=Climate change impacts, adaptive capacity, and vulnerability of European forest ecosystems&amp;author=M Lindner&amp;author=M Maraschek&amp;author=S Netherer&amp;volume=259&amp;publication_year=2010&amp;pages=698-709&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="TPW017C42"><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Liu W, Saint DA (2002) A new quantitative method of real time reverse transcription polymerase chain reaction assay based on simulation of polymerase chain reaction kinetics. Anal Biochem
302:52–59. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1006/abio.2001.5530" ext-link-type="uri">doi:10.1006/abio.2001.5530</ext-link></named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1006/abio.2001.5530"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="11846375"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Anal Biochem&amp;title=A new quantitative method of real time reverse transcription polymerase chain reaction assay based on simulation of polymerase chain reaction kinetics&amp;author=W Liu&amp;author=DA Saint&amp;volume=302&amp;publication_year=2002&amp;pages=52-59&amp;pmid=11846375&amp;doi=10.1006/abio.2001.5530&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="TPW017C43"><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">MacAlister CA, Ohashi-Ito K, Bergmann DC (2007) Transcription factor control of asymmetric cell divisions that establish the stomatal lineage. Nature
445:537–540. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/nature05491" ext-link-type="uri">doi:10.1038/nature05491</ext-link></named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1038/nature05491"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="17183265"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Nature&amp;title=Transcription factor control of asymmetric cell divisions that establish the stomatal lineage&amp;author=CA MacAlister&amp;author=K Ohashi-Ito&amp;author=DC Bergmann&amp;volume=445&amp;publication_year=2007&amp;pages=537-540&amp;pmid=17183265&amp;doi=10.1038/nature05491&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="TPW017C44"><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Marron N, Delay D, Petit JM, Dreyer E, Kahlem G, Delmotte FM, Brignolas F (2002) Physiological traits of two <italic>Populus</italic> × <italic>euramericana</italic> clones, Luisa Avanzo and Dorskamp, during a water stress and re-watering cycle. Tree Physiol
22:849–858. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/treephys/22.12.849" ext-link-type="uri">doi:10.1093/treephys/22.12.849</ext-link></named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1093/treephys/22.12.849"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="12184974"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Tree Physiol&amp;title=Physiological traits of two Populus × euramericana clones, Luisa Avanzo and Dorskamp, during a water stress and re-watering cycle&amp;author=N Marron&amp;author=D Delay&amp;author=JM Petit&amp;author=E Dreyer&amp;author=G Kahlem&amp;volume=22&amp;publication_year=2002&amp;pages=849-858&amp;pmid=12184974&amp;doi=10.1093/treephys/22.12.849&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="TPW017C45"><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Marron N, Villar M, Dreyer E, Delay D, Boudouresque E, Petit J-M, Delmotte FM, Guehl JM, Brignolas F (2005) Diversity of leaf traits related to productivity in 31 <italic>Populus deltoides</italic> × <italic>Populus nigra</italic> clones. Tree Physiol
25:425–435. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/treephys/25.4.425" ext-link-type="uri">doi:10.1093/treephys/25.4.425</ext-link></named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1093/treephys/25.4.425"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="15687091"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Tree Physiol&amp;title=Diversity of leaf traits related to productivity in 31 Populus deltoides × Populus nigra clones&amp;author=N Marron&amp;author=M Villar&amp;author=E Dreyer&amp;author=D Delay&amp;author=E Boudouresque&amp;volume=25&amp;publication_year=2005&amp;pages=425-435&amp;pmid=15687091&amp;doi=10.1093/treephys/25.4.425&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="TPW017C46"><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Masle J, Gilmore SR, Farquhar GD (2005) The <italic>ERECTA</italic> gene regulates plant transpiration efficiency in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>. Nature
436:866–870. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/nature03835" ext-link-type="uri">doi:10.1038/nature03835</ext-link></named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1038/nature03835"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="16007076"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Nature&amp;title=The ERECTA gene regulates plant transpiration efficiency in Arabidopsis&amp;author=J Masle&amp;author=SR Gilmore&amp;author=GD Farquhar&amp;volume=436&amp;publication_year=2005&amp;pages=866-870&amp;pmid=16007076&amp;doi=10.1038/nature03835&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="TPW017C47"><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">McClintock JN, Edenberg HJ (2006) Effects of filtering by Present call on analysis of microarray experiments. BMC Bioinformatics
7:49
<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1186/1471-2105-7-49" ext-link-type="uri">doi:10.1186/1471-2105-7-49</ext-link></named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1186/1471-2105-7-49"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC1409797"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="16448562"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=BMC Bioinformatics&amp;title=Effects of filtering by Present call on analysis of microarray experiments&amp;author=JN McClintock&amp;author=HJ Edenberg&amp;volume=7&amp;publication_year=2006&amp;pages=49&amp;pmid=16448562&amp;doi=10.1186/1471-2105-7-49&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="TPW017C48"><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Monclus R, Dreyer E, Delmotte FM et al.  (2005) Productivity, leaf traits and carbon isotope discrimination in 29 <italic>Populus deltoides</italic> × <italic>P. nigra</italic> clones. New Phytol
167:53–62. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1469-8137.2005.01407.x" ext-link-type="uri">doi:10.1111/j.1469-8137.2005.01407.x</ext-link></named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1111/j.1469-8137.2005.01407.x"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="15948829"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=New Phytol&amp;title=Productivity, leaf traits and carbon isotope discrimination in 29 Populus deltoides × P. nigra clones&amp;author=R Monclus&amp;author=E Dreyer&amp;author=FM Delmotte&amp;volume=167&amp;publication_year=2005&amp;pages=53-62&amp;pmid=15948829&amp;doi=10.1111/j.1469-8137.2005.01407.x&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="TPW017C49"><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Monclus R, Dreyer E, Villar M et al.  (2006) Impact of drought on productivity and water use efficiency in 29 genotypes of <italic>Populus deltoides</italic> × <italic>Populus nigra</italic>. New Phytol
169:765–777. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1469-8137.2005.01630.x" ext-link-type="uri">doi:10.1111/j.1469-8137.2005.01630.x</ext-link></named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1111/j.1469-8137.2005.01630.x"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="16441757"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=New Phytol&amp;title=Impact of drought on productivity and water use efficiency in 29 genotypes of Populus deltoides × Populus nigra&amp;author=R Monclus&amp;author=E Dreyer&amp;author=M Villar&amp;volume=169&amp;publication_year=2006&amp;pages=765-777&amp;pmid=16441757&amp;doi=10.1111/j.1469-8137.2005.01630.x&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="TPW017C50"><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Monclus R, Leplé J-C, Bastien C, Bert P-F, Villar M, Marron N, Brignolas F, Jorge V (2012) Integrating genome annotation and QTL position to identify candidate genes for productivity, architecture and water-use efficiency in <italic>Populus</italic> spp. BMC Plant Biol
12:173
<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1186/1471-2229-12-173" ext-link-type="uri">doi:10.1186/1471-2229-12-173</ext-link></named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1186/1471-2229-12-173"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC3520807"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="23013168"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=BMC Plant Biol&amp;title=Integrating genome annotation and QTL position to identify candidate genes for productivity, architecture and water-use efficiency in Populus spp&amp;author=R Monclus&amp;author=J-C Leplé&amp;author=C Bastien&amp;author=P-F Bert&amp;author=M Villar&amp;volume=12&amp;publication_year=2012&amp;pages=173&amp;pmid=23013168&amp;doi=10.1186/1471-2229-12-173&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="TPW017C52"><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Nilson SE, Assmann SM (2007) The control of transpiration. Insights from <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>. Plant Physiol
143:19–27. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1104/pp.106.093161" ext-link-type="uri">doi:10.1104/pp.106.093161</ext-link></named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1104/pp.106.093161"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC1761994"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="17210910"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Plant Physiol&amp;title=The control of transpiration. Insights from Arabidopsis&amp;author=SE Nilson&amp;author=SM Assmann&amp;volume=143&amp;publication_year=2007&amp;pages=19-27&amp;pmid=17210910&amp;doi=10.1104/pp.106.093161&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="TPW017C54"><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Radin JW, Lu Z, Percy RG, Zeiger E (1994) Genetic variability for stomatal conductance in Pima cotton and its relation to improvements of heat adaptation. Proc Natl Acad Sci USA
91:7217–7221. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1073/pnas.91.15.7217" ext-link-type="uri">doi:10.1073/pnas.91.15.7217</ext-link></named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1073/pnas.91.15.7217"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC44370"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="11607487"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Proc Natl Acad Sci USA&amp;title=Genetic variability for stomatal conductance in Pima cotton and its relation to improvements of heat adaptation&amp;author=JW Radin&amp;author=Z Lu&amp;author=RG Percy&amp;author=E Zeiger&amp;volume=91&amp;publication_year=1994&amp;pages=7217-7221&amp;pmid=11607487&amp;doi=10.1073/pnas.91.15.7217&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="TPW017C55"><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Rae AM, Robinson KM, Street NR, Taylor G (2004) Morphological and physiological traits influencing biomass productivity in short-rotation coppice poplar. Can J For Res
34:1488–1498. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1139/x04-033" ext-link-type="uri">doi:10.1139/x04-033</ext-link></named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Can J For Res&amp;title=Morphological and physiological traits influencing biomass productivity in short-rotation coppice poplar&amp;author=AM Rae&amp;author=KM Robinson&amp;author=NR Street&amp;author=G Taylor&amp;volume=34&amp;publication_year=2004&amp;pages=1488-1498&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="TPW017C56"><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Rae AM, Street NR, Robinson KM, Harris N, Taylor G (2009) Five QTL hotspots for yield in short rotation coppice bioenergy poplar: The Poplar Biomass Loci. BMC Plant Biol
9:23
<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1186/1471-2229-9-23" ext-link-type="uri">doi:10.1186/1471-2229-9-23</ext-link></named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1186/1471-2229-9-23"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC2657785"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="19245718"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=BMC Plant Biol&amp;title=Five QTL hotspots for yield in short rotation coppice bioenergy poplar: The Poplar Biomass Loci&amp;author=AM Rae&amp;author=NR Street&amp;author=KM Robinson&amp;author=N Harris&amp;author=G Taylor&amp;volume=9&amp;publication_year=2009&amp;pages=23&amp;pmid=19245718&amp;doi=10.1186/1471-2229-9-23&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="TPW017C57"><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">R Development Core Team (2014)
R: a language and environment for statistical computing. R Foundation for Statistical Computing, Vienna, Austria; 
<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.R-project.org" ext-link-type="uri">http://www.R-project.org</ext-link>.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="R Development Core Team (2014) R: a language and environment for statistical computing. R Foundation for Statistical Computing, Vienna, Austria; http://www.R-project.org."/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="TPW017C58"><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Regier N, Streb S, Cocozza C, Schaub M, Cherubini P, Zeeman SC, Frey B (2009) Drought tolerance of two black poplar (<italic>Populus nigra</italic> L.) clones: contribution of carbohydrates and oxidative stress defence. Plant Cell Environ
32:1724–1736. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1365-3040.2009.02030.x" ext-link-type="uri">doi:10.1111/j.1365-3040.2009.02030.x</ext-link></named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1111/j.1365-3040.2009.02030.x"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="19671097"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Plant Cell Environ&amp;title=Drought tolerance of two black poplar (Populus nigra L.) clones: contribution of carbohydrates and oxidative stress defence&amp;author=N Regier&amp;author=S Streb&amp;author=C Cocozza&amp;author=M Schaub&amp;author=P Cherubini&amp;volume=32&amp;publication_year=2009&amp;pages=1724-1736&amp;pmid=19671097&amp;doi=10.1111/j.1365-3040.2009.02030.x&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="TPW017C60"><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Roussel M, Dreyer E, Montpied P, Le-Provost G, Guehl J-M, Brendel O (2009) The diversity of <sup>13</sup>C isotope discrimination in a <italic>Quercus robur</italic> full-sib family is associated with differences in intrinsic water use efficiency, transpiration efficiency, and stomatal conductance. J Exp Bot
60:2419–2431. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/jxb/erp100" ext-link-type="uri">doi:10.1093/jxb/erp100</ext-link></named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1093/jxb/erp100"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="19380420"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=J Exp Bot&amp;title=The diversity of 13C isotope discrimination in a Quercus robur full-sib family is associated with differences in intrinsic water use efficiency, transpiration efficiency, and stomatal conductance&amp;author=M Roussel&amp;author=E Dreyer&amp;author=P Montpied&amp;author=G Le-Provost&amp;author=J-M Guehl&amp;volume=60&amp;publication_year=2009&amp;pages=2419-2431&amp;pmid=19380420&amp;doi=10.1093/jxb/erp100&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="TPW017C61"><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Schafleitner R, Gutierrez Rosales RO, Gaudin A et al.  (2007) Capturing candidate drought tolerance traits in two native Andean potato clones by transcription profiling of field grown plants under water stress. Plant Physiol Biochem
45:673–690. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.plaphy.2007.06.003" ext-link-type="uri">doi:10.1016/j.plaphy.2007.06.003</ext-link></named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/j.plaphy.2007.06.003"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="17764965"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Plant Physiol Biochem&amp;title=Capturing candidate drought tolerance traits in two native Andean potato clones by transcription profiling of field grown plants under water stress&amp;author=R Schafleitner&amp;author=RO Gutierrez Rosales&amp;author=A Gaudin&amp;volume=45&amp;publication_year=2007&amp;pages=673-690&amp;pmid=17764965&amp;doi=10.1016/j.plaphy.2007.06.003&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="TPW017C62"><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Scrimgeour CM, Robinson D, Smith KA, Cresser MS (2004) Stable isotope analysis and applications. Soil and environmental analysis modern instrumental techniques.
Marcel Dekker, Inc.,
New York, NY, pp 381–431.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="title=Stable isotope analysis and applications. Soil and environmental analysis modern instrumental techniques&amp;author=CM Scrimgeour&amp;author=D Robinson&amp;author=KA Smith&amp;author=MS Cresser&amp;publication_year=2004&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="TPW017C63"><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Shpak ED, McAbee JM, Pillitteri LJ, Torii KU (2007) Stomatal patterning and differentiation by synergistic interactions of receptor kinases. Science
309:290–293. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1126/science.1109710" ext-link-type="uri">doi:10.1126/science.1109710</ext-link></named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1126/science.1109710"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="16002616"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Science&amp;title=Stomatal patterning and differentiation by synergistic interactions of receptor kinases&amp;author=ED Shpak&amp;author=JM McAbee&amp;author=LJ Pillitteri&amp;author=KU Torii&amp;volume=309&amp;publication_year=2007&amp;pages=290-293&amp;pmid=16002616&amp;doi=10.1126/science.1109710&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="TPW017C64"><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Smyth GK. (2004) Linear models and empirical Bayes methods for assessing differential expression in microarray experiments. Stat Appl Genet Mol Biol
3:1–25. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.2202/1544-6115.1027" ext-link-type="uri">doi:10.2202/1544-6115.1027</ext-link></named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.2202/1544-6115.1027"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="16646809"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Stat Appl Genet Mol Biol&amp;title=Linear models and empirical Bayes methods for assessing differential expression in microarray experiments&amp;author=GK Smyth&amp;volume=3&amp;publication_year=2004&amp;pages=1-25&amp;pmid=16646809&amp;doi=10.2202/1544-6115.1027&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="TPW017C65"><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Solberg S. (2004) Summer drought: a driver for crown condition and mortality of Norway spruce in Norway. Forest Pathol
34:93–104. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1439-0329.2004.00351.x" ext-link-type="uri">doi:10.1111/j.1439-0329.2004.00351.x</ext-link></named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Forest Pathol&amp;title=Summer drought: a driver for crown condition and mortality of Norway spruce in Norway&amp;author=S Solberg&amp;volume=34&amp;publication_year=2004&amp;pages=93-104&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="TPW017C66"><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Sparks JP, Black RA (1999) Regulation of water loss in populations of <italic>Populus trichocarpa</italic>: the role of stomatal control in preventing xylem cavitation. Tree Physiol
19:453–459. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/treephys/19.7.453" ext-link-type="uri">doi:10.1093/treephys/19.7.453</ext-link></named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1093/treephys/19.7.453"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="12651551"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Tree Physiol&amp;title=Regulation of water loss in populations of Populus trichocarpa: the role of stomatal control in preventing xylem cavitation&amp;author=JP Sparks&amp;author=RA Black&amp;volume=19&amp;publication_year=1999&amp;pages=453-459&amp;pmid=12651551&amp;doi=10.1093/treephys/19.7.453&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="TPW017C67"><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Street NR, Skogström O, Sjödin A, Tucker J, Rodríguez-Acosta M, Nilsson P, Jansson S, Taylor G (2006) The genetics and genomics of the drought response in <italic>Populus</italic>. Plant J
48:321–341. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1365-313X.2006.02864.x" ext-link-type="uri">doi:10.1111/j.1365-313X.2006.02864.x</ext-link></named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1111/j.1365-313X.2006.02864.x"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="17005011"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Plant J&amp;title=The genetics and genomics of the drought response in Populus&amp;author=NR Street&amp;author=O Skogström&amp;author=A Sjödin&amp;author=J Tucker&amp;author=M Rodríguez-Acosta&amp;volume=48&amp;publication_year=2006&amp;pages=321-341&amp;pmid=17005011&amp;doi=10.1111/j.1365-313X.2006.02864.x&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="TPW017C68"><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Tardieu F, Tuberosa R (2010) Dissection and modelling of abiotic stress tolerance in plants. Curr Opin Plant Biol
13:206–212. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.pbi.2009.12.012" ext-link-type="uri">doi:10.1016/j.pbi.2009.12.012</ext-link></named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/j.pbi.2009.12.012"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="20097596"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Curr Opin Plant Biol&amp;title=Dissection and modelling of abiotic stress tolerance in plants&amp;author=F Tardieu&amp;author=R Tuberosa&amp;volume=13&amp;publication_year=2010&amp;pages=206-212&amp;pmid=20097596&amp;doi=10.1016/j.pbi.2009.12.012&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="TPW017C69"><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Taylor G. (2002) <italic>Populus</italic>: <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> for forestry. Do we need a model tree. Ann Bot
90:681–689. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/aob/mcf255" ext-link-type="uri">doi:10.1093/aob/mcf255</ext-link></named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1093/aob/mcf255"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC4240366"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="12451023"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Ann Bot&amp;title=Populus: Arabidopsis for forestry. Do we need a model tree&amp;author=G Taylor&amp;volume=90&amp;publication_year=2002&amp;pages=681-689&amp;pmid=12451023&amp;doi=10.1093/aob/mcf255&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="TPW017C70"><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Thimm O, Bläsing O, Nagel A, Meyer S, Krüger P, Selbig J, Müller LA (2004) MAPMAN: a user-driven tool to display genomics data sets onto diagrams of metabolic pathways and other biological processes. Plant J
37:914–939. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1365-313X.2004.02016.x" ext-link-type="uri">doi:10.1111/j.1365-313X.2004.02016.x</ext-link></named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1111/j.1365-313x.2004.02016.x"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="14996223"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Plant J&amp;title=MAPMAN: a user-driven tool to display genomics data sets onto diagrams of metabolic pathways and other biological processes&amp;author=O Thimm&amp;author=O Bläsing&amp;author=A Nagel&amp;author=S Meyer&amp;author=P Krüger&amp;volume=37&amp;publication_year=2004&amp;pages=914-939&amp;pmid=14996223&amp;doi=10.1111/j.1365-313x.2004.02016.x&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="TPW017C71"><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Torii KU. (2015) Stomatal differentiation: the beginning and the end. Curr Opin Plant Biol
28:16–22. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.pbi.2015.08.005" ext-link-type="uri">doi:10.1016/j.pbi.2015.08.005</ext-link></named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/j.pbi.2015.08.005"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="26344486"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Curr Opin Plant Biol&amp;title=Stomatal differentiation: the beginning and the end&amp;author=KU Torii&amp;volume=28&amp;publication_year=2015&amp;pages=16-22&amp;pmid=26344486&amp;doi=10.1016/j.pbi.2015.08.005&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="TPW017C72"><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Tschaplinski TJ, Tuskan GA, Sewell MM, Gebre GM, Donald ETI, Pendleyi C (2006) Phenotypic variation and quantitative trait locus identification for osmotic potential in an interspecific hybrid inbred F<sub>2</sub> poplar pedigree grown in contrasting environments. Tree Physiol
26:595–604. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/treephys/26.5.595" ext-link-type="uri">doi:10.1093/treephys/26.5.595</ext-link></named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1093/treephys/26.5.595"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="16452073"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Tree Physiol&amp;title=Phenotypic variation and quantitative trait locus identification for osmotic potential in an interspecific hybrid inbred F2 poplar pedigree grown in contrasting environments&amp;author=TJ Tschaplinski&amp;author=GA Tuskan&amp;author=MM Sewell&amp;author=GM Gebre&amp;author=ETI Donald&amp;volume=26&amp;publication_year=2006&amp;pages=595-604&amp;pmid=16452073&amp;doi=10.1093/treephys/26.5.595&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="TPW017C73"><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Tuskan GA, DiFazio S, Teichmann T (2004) Poplar genomics is getting popular: the impact of the poplar genome project on tree research. Plant Biol
6:2–4. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1055/s-2003-44715" ext-link-type="uri">doi:10.1055/s-2003-44715</ext-link></named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1055/s-2003-44715"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="15095128"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Plant Biol&amp;title=Poplar genomics is getting popular: the impact of the poplar genome project on tree research&amp;author=GA Tuskan&amp;author=S DiFazio&amp;author=T Teichmann&amp;volume=6&amp;publication_year=2004&amp;pages=2-4&amp;pmid=15095128&amp;doi=10.1055/s-2003-44715&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="TPW017C74"><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Tuskan GA, DiFazio S, Jansson S et al.  (2006) The genome of black cottonwood, <italic>Populus trichocarpa</italic> (Torr. &amp; Gray). Science
313:1596–1604. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1126/science.1128691" ext-link-type="uri">doi:10.1126/science.1128691</ext-link></named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1126/science.1128691"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="16973872"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Science&amp;title=The genome of black cottonwood, Populus trichocarpa (Torr. &amp; Gray)&amp;author=GA Tuskan&amp;author=S DiFazio&amp;author=S Jansson&amp;volume=313&amp;publication_year=2006&amp;pages=1596-1604&amp;pmid=16973872&amp;doi=10.1126/science.1128691&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="TPW017C75"><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Valladares F, Martinez-Ferri E, Balaguer L, Perez-Corona E, Manrique E (2000) Low leaf-level response to light and nutrients in Mediterranean evergreen oaks: a conservative resource-use strategy. New Phytol
148:79–91. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1046/j.1469-8137.2000.00737.x" ext-link-type="uri">doi:10.1046/j.1469-8137.2000.00737.x</ext-link></named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1046/j.1469-8137.2000.00737.x"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="33863045"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=New Phytol&amp;title=Low leaf-level response to light and nutrients in Mediterranean evergreen oaks: a conservative resource-use strategy&amp;author=F Valladares&amp;author=E Martinez-Ferri&amp;author=L Balaguer&amp;author=E Perez-Corona&amp;author=E Manrique&amp;volume=148&amp;publication_year=2000&amp;pages=79-91&amp;pmid=33863045&amp;doi=10.1046/j.1469-8137.2000.00737.x&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="TPW017C76"><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Vanden Broeck A. (2003) EUFORGEN Technical Guidelines for genetic conservation
and use for black poplar (<italic>Populus nigra</italic>).
International Plant Genetic Resources Institute,
Rome, pp 1–6.</named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="title=EUFORGEN Technical Guidelines for genetic conservation&amp;author=A Vanden Broeck&amp;publication_year=2003&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="TPW017C77"><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Viger M, Rodriguez-Acosta M, Rae AM, Morison JIL, Taylor G (2013) Toward improved drought tolerance in bioenergy crops: QTL for carbon isotope composition and stomatal conductance in <italic>Populus</italic>. Food Energy Secur
2:220–236. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/fes3.39" ext-link-type="uri">doi:10.1002/fes3.39</ext-link></named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Food Energy Secur&amp;title=Toward improved drought tolerance in bioenergy crops: QTL for carbon isotope composition and stomatal conductance in Populus&amp;author=M Viger&amp;author=M Rodriguez-Acosta&amp;author=AM Rae&amp;author=JIL Morison&amp;author=G Taylor&amp;volume=2&amp;publication_year=2013&amp;pages=220-236&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="TPW017C78"><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Voltas J, Serrano L, Hernández M, Pemán J (2006) Carbon isotope discrimination, gas exchange and stem growth of four Euramerican hybrid poplars under different watering regimes. New Forests
31: 435–451. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s11056-005-0879-7" ext-link-type="uri">doi:10.1007/s11056-005-0879-7</ext-link></named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=New Forests&amp;title=Carbon isotope discrimination, gas exchange and stem growth of four Euramerican hybrid poplars under different watering regimes&amp;author=J Voltas&amp;author=L Serrano&amp;author=M Hernández&amp;author=J Pemán&amp;volume=31&amp;publication_year=2006&amp;pages=435-451&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="TPW017C79"><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Walia H, Wilson C, Condamine P et al.  (2005) Comparative transcriptional profiling of two contrasting rice genotypes under salinity stress during the vegetative growth stage. Plant Physiol
139:822–835. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1104/pp.105.065961" ext-link-type="uri">doi:10.1104/pp.105.065961</ext-link></named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1104/pp.105.065961"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC1255998"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="16183841"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Plant Physiol&amp;title=Comparative transcriptional profiling of two contrasting rice genotypes under salinity stress during the vegetative growth stage&amp;author=H Walia&amp;author=C Wilson&amp;author=P Condamine&amp;volume=139&amp;publication_year=2005&amp;pages=822-835&amp;pmid=16183841&amp;doi=10.1104/pp.105.065961&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="TPW017C80"><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Walia H, Wilson C, Zeng L, Ismail AM, Condamine P, Close TJ (2007) Genome-wide transcriptional analysis of salinity stressed <italic>japonica</italic> and <italic>indica</italic> rice genotypes during panicle initiation stage. Plant Mol Biol
63:609–623. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s11103-006-9112-0" ext-link-type="uri">doi:10.1007/s11103-006-9112-0</ext-link></named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1007/s11103-006-9112-0"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmcid" xlink:href="PMC1805040"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="17160619"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Plant Mol Biol&amp;title=Genome-wide transcriptional analysis of salinity stressed japonica and indica rice genotypes during panicle initiation stage&amp;author=H Walia&amp;author=C Wilson&amp;author=L Zeng&amp;author=AM Ismail&amp;author=P Condamine&amp;volume=63&amp;publication_year=2007&amp;pages=609-623&amp;pmid=17160619&amp;doi=10.1007/s11103-006-9112-0&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="TPW017C81"><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Wilkins O, Waldron L, Nahal H, Provart NJ, Campbell MM (2009) Genotype and time of day shape the <italic>Populus</italic> drought response. Plant J
60:703–715. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1365-313X.2009.03993.x" ext-link-type="uri">doi:10.1111/j.1365-313X.2009.03993.x</ext-link></named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1111/j.1365-313X.2009.03993.x"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="19682285"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=Plant J&amp;title=Genotype and time of day shape the Populus drought response&amp;author=O Wilkins&amp;author=L Waldron&amp;author=H Nahal&amp;author=NJ Provart&amp;author=MM Campbell&amp;volume=60&amp;publication_year=2009&amp;pages=703-715&amp;pmid=19682285&amp;doi=10.1111/j.1365-313X.2009.03993.x&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="TPW017C82"><mixed-citation><named-content content-type="citation-string">Woodward FI, Lake JA, Quick WP (2002) Stomatal development and CO<sub>2</sub>: ecological consequences. New Phytol
153:477–484. <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1046/j.0028-646X.2001.00338.x" ext-link-type="uri">doi:10.1046/j.0028-646X.2001.00338.x</ext-link></named-content><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1046/j.0028-646X.2001.00338.x"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="pmid" xlink:href="33863227"/><ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="google-scholar" xlink:href="journal=New Phytol&amp;title=Stomatal development and CO2: ecological consequences&amp;author=FI Woodward&amp;author=JA Lake&amp;author=WP Quick&amp;volume=153&amp;publication_year=2002&amp;pages=477-484&amp;pmid=33863227&amp;doi=10.1046/j.0028-646X.2001.00338.x&amp;"/></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></sec></sec><sec id="_ad93_" xml:lang="en" sec-type="associated-data" disp-level="1"><title>Associated Data</title><sec id="_adsm93_" xml:lang="en" sec-type="supplementary-materials" disp-level="2"><title>Supplementary Materials</title><supplementary-material id="db_ds_supplementary-material1_reqid_" position="float"><?disp-level 2?><caption><title>Supplementary Data</title></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="supp_36_7_909__index.html" mimetype="text" mime-subtype="html"><?cloudpmc-path d4bd/4969554/81941f79c840/supp_36_7_909__index.html?><?cloudpmc-bucket app?><?size 1713?></media><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="supp_tpw017_tpw017supp.docx" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.wordprocessingml.document"><?cloudpmc-path d4bd/4969554/e12554b539b7/supp_tpw017_tpw017supp.docx?><?cloudpmc-bucket app?><?size 16665?></media><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="supp_tpw017_tpw017supp_fig1.jpg" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="jpeg"><?cloudpmc-path d4bd/4969554/91e48d952854/supp_tpw017_tpw017supp_fig1.jpg?><?cloudpmc-bucket app?><?size 1244908?></media><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="supp_tpw017_tpw017supp_fig2.jpg" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="jpeg"><?cloudpmc-path d4bd/4969554/31c15b8055a4/supp_tpw017_tpw017supp_fig2.jpg?><?cloudpmc-bucket app?><?size 1005437?></media><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="supp_tpw017_tpw017supp_fig3.jpg" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="jpeg"><?cloudpmc-path d4bd/4969554/f3bc3c9569ef/supp_tpw017_tpw017supp_fig3.jpg?><?cloudpmc-bucket app?><?size 661295?></media><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="supp_tpw017_tpw017supp_Table_S1S2S3S5.docx" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.wordprocessingml.document"><?cloudpmc-path d4bd/4969554/c6c5060cf32e/supp_tpw017_tpw017supp_Table_S1S2S3S5.docx?><?cloudpmc-bucket app?><?size 30060?></media><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="supp_tpw017_tpw017supp_Table_S4.xlsx" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.spreadsheetml.sheet"><?cloudpmc-path d4bd/4969554/9114221d0a3c/supp_tpw017_tpw017supp_Table_S4.xlsx?><?cloudpmc-bucket app?><?size 20463?></media><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="supp_tpw017_tpw017supp_Table_S6.xlsx" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.spreadsheetml.sheet"><?cloudpmc-path d4bd/4969554/3260963faea7/supp_tpw017_tpw017supp_Table_S6.xlsx?><?cloudpmc-bucket app?><?size 8001551?></media><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="supp_tpw017_tpw017supp_Table_S7.xls" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.ms-office"><?cloudpmc-path d4bd/4969554/f2c21f0a5c3c/supp_tpw017_tpw017supp_Table_S7.xls?><?cloudpmc-bucket app?><?size 1175552?></media><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="supp_tpw017_tpw017supp_Table_S8.xlsx" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.spreadsheetml.sheet"><?cloudpmc-path d4bd/4969554/c7209a24f6a6/supp_tpw017_tpw017supp_Table_S8.xlsx?><?cloudpmc-bucket app?><?size 46028?></media></supplementary-material></sec></sec></body></article>